<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Babilon, a part of the Seconde vveeke of Guillaume de Saluste seigneur du Bartas, with the commentarie, and marginall notes of S.G.S. Englished by William L'Isle</title>
            <title>Seconde sepmaine. Day 2. Part 2. English</title>
            <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur, 1544-1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110840</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846308</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11268</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11406)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11268)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 352:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Babilon, a part of the Seconde vveeke of Guillaume de Saluste seigneur du Bartas, with the commentarie, and marginall notes of S.G.S. Englished by William L'Isle</title>
                  <title>Seconde sepmaine. Day 2. Part 2. English</title>
                  <author>Du Bartas, Guillaume de Salluste, seigneur, 1544-1590.</author>
                  <author>Lisle, William, 1579?-1637.</author>
                  <author>Goulart, Simon, 1543-1628.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 66, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ed. Bollifant, for Richard Watkins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of book 2 of day 2 of: La seconde sepmaine.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>S.G.S. = Simon Goulart de Senlis.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with imprint dated 1596.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis --  History of Biblical events --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11268:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11268:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BABILON, A PART OF THE SECONDE WEEKE OF GVILLAVME DE SALVSTE SEIGNEVR DV BARTAS, With the Commentarie, and marginall Notes of S. G. S.</p>
            <p>Engliſhed by WILLIAM L'ISLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omne tulit punctum qui miſcuit vtile dulci.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Ed. Bollifant, for Richard Watkins. 1595</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11268:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11268:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, CHARLES LORD HOWARD, BARON OF</hi> Effingham, Knight of the most renowmed order of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, one of hir Maiesties priuie Councell, and Lord high Admirall of England, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Aying how neere it concernes your Honourable Charge, what ſtraungers paſſe the Seas into England, I was thereby, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in humble duty, moued, to giue your Lordſhip firſt intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of this Gentilman, whom I haue newly tranſported out of Fraunce: and alſo thought it neceſſarie to craue your fauorable protection of him in this his trauell. A woorthie man is he (my Lord) in his owne country, howſoeuer here diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and one of the ſonnes of that noble and diuine Poet LE SIEVR DV BARTAS; in my ſimple iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the propereſt, and beſt learned of them all, I am ſure the beſt affected to England, and the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Empereſſe thereof: for which cauſe I made ſpeciall choiſe of him, and doe therefore the rather hope to finde fauour on his behalfe with your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable
<pb facs="tcp:11268:3"/>
Lordſhip; whoſe loyaltie to the Crowne, the Prince by truſt of ſo high an office, whoſe loue to the land, the people by ioint-conſent of daily-felt vertues, haue ſo fully witneſſed, that the fame thereof hath ſpred it ſelfe far beyond that your admirable Regiment. In ſo much as this gentle ſtranger, though he were at the firſt vnwilling, Vliſſes-like, to leaue his natiue ſoile, eſpecially now in this dangerous ſea-faring time, while all the world is in a maner troubled with Spaniſh Fleetes; yet after he called to minde what he had heard and written of the mightie Goddeſſe of the Engliſh O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, and who there ſwaied the Trident vnder hir, truſting vpon ſuch a Neptune, he went aboord with a good courage, &amp; doubting not at al but that the proud Spaniſh Caracks, if they be not yet ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently diſmaid by the wracke they ſuffered in their former aduenture, but dare againe attempt the like, be they neuer ſo many more or greater than they were (if more and greater they can be) ſhall againe, by the grace of God, directing (as before) the courage and wiſedome of Englands renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Admirall, be diſperſed ouer the frowning face of our diſdainfull Seas, &amp; dronken with ſalt waues regorge the bodies of their preſumptuous Pilots.
<pb facs="tcp:11268:3"/>
And ſo (my Lord) with a fauorable winde, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing directly from the French Helicon, by the ſafe conduit of your Honourable name, and helpe of the Muſes, at length I landed my ſtranger in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Where ſince his arriuall he hath gladly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred diuers of his elder brethren, that were come ouer before, ſome in a princely Scottiſh at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, others in faire Engliſh habits; and to th' entent he might the better enioy their companie, who by this time had almoſt forgotten their French, he was deſirous to learne Engliſh of me: therefore I kept him a while about me, was his teacher at home, and enterpreter abroad; and now that he hath gotten ſuch a ſmattering of the toong, as he can (ſo as he can) ſpeake for himſelfe, may it pleaſe your good L. to talke with him at your leiſure: though I know you vnderſtand very well his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſpeech, I am of opinion it wil much delight you to heare him vtter ſuch counterfait Engliſh, as in ſo little time I was able to teach him. He can ſay ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the godly gouernment of good princes, &amp; the wicked practiſes of Tyrants, as well in compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as maintaining a Scepter; both woorthy your L. hearing for the manner ſake, though the matter be not vnknowne to your wiſdome. But ſom other
<pb facs="tcp:11268:4"/>
things he doth report verie ſtrange, as of NIM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROD, that was the firſt Tyrant of the world, after the time of Noah, the firſt Admiral of the worlde: his aſpiring minde &amp; practiſes in ſeeking the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples fauour, his proud and ſubtle attempt in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Tower of Babel, &amp; Gods iuſt puniſhment thereof in confounding the language of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Verie truly reckoneth he (that which few do conſider) the great and manifold inconueniences that are befallen mankinde by the diuerſitie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tongs. Further he can tel of ſpeech in general, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man ſpeake by nature, or haue but onelie an aptnes to ſpeake by vſe, &amp; whether any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture haue the like: as for ſeuerall ſpeeches, he can prooue, with many goodly reaſons, which is the beſt &amp; moſt ancient of them all; what altereth each toong, what continueth each in account, what lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages are in greateſt regard now-adaies, &amp; what Authors haue moſt excelled in them. And vpon occaſion of the Engliſh toong, my Lord, he ſetteth out in ſuch maner the Queenes princely maieſtie, hir learning, wiſdome, eloquence, and other excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertues, that I know your noble &amp; loyall hart wil greatly reioice to heare it, at the mouth of ſuch a ſtranger. The reſt, if it be more curious, then, for
<pb facs="tcp:11268:4"/>
the ſtates waightie affaires, your L. may intend to hear, I wiſh referred vnto thoſe goodly yong gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, your noble &amp; fatherlike-minded Sons, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after your L.I do moſt of all honor: there ſhal they find profit ſo blended with pleaſure, learning with delight, as it may eaſilie winne their harts, alreadie vertuouſly aſpiring, from the wanton and faining Cantoes of other Syren-Poets (wherewith manie yoong gentlemen, and chiefely thoſe of greateſt hope, are long and dangerouſly miſ-led) vnto a further acquaintance with this heauenly-poeticall writer of the truth: who is now growne into ſuch a liking of this countrey, chiefely for the peaceable gouernment thereof (bleſſed be that Gouernour) and free courſe of the Goſpell (God continue it, and ſende the like into Fraunce) that he is deſirous to become a Freedenizen; and hoping further to to be an eie-witnes of Gods woonderfull mercies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this Land, whereof in Fraunce he ſpake but by heare-ſaie, to behold that pretious Northren Pearle, and kiſſe hir Scepter-bearing hand, whoſe woorthy praiſe he hath ſoong ſo ſweetely, he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie beſeech your gratious fauour to be enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed, which if it may pleaſe you to graunt (my Lorde) vouchſafing alſo the patronage of him;
<pb facs="tcp:11268:5"/>
that vnder ſeale of your honourable name he may eſcape the carping cenſures of curious fault-fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and enioy all honours, priuiledges, liberties and lawes, that belong eu'n to the naturall inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this noble Iſle, my ſelfe will vndertake to Fine for him, at leaſt harty praiers for your daily encreaſe of honour, and all ſuch obedience, as it ſhall pleaſe your L. to impoſe:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Whoſe I reſt euer at commaund. VVilliam L'iſle.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11268:5"/>
            <head>Th' Argument of the two firſt dayes of the ſecond weeke of Guil. de SALVSTE Seigneur Du Bartas.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſes ſaith, that in ſixe daies God created the heauen and the earth, the ſea, and all in them contained, then reſted the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day, &amp;c. Which the Poet hath at large expounded in his firſt wéeke.<note n="*" place="margin">The whole ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond weeke.</note> And hauing with ſo luckie hand begun, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth (by the grace of God) to follow foorth ſo excellent a worke, and in a ſecond wéeke to ſet out the ſtate of the world from Adam to the latter day, adioyning thereunto euen a liuely deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of th' euerlaſting Saboth: ſo now he giueth vs the two firſt daies, to each of them allotting foure bookes. The firſt day may be called Adam, and repreſenteth the ſtate of the firſt man, before and after the fall, euen to his death, and of his poſteritie to the flood. The ſecond day may be called Noe, and containeth the ſtate of the world after the flood to the time of Abraham: ſo that here we haue a learned and holy paraphraſe vpon a part of the firſt booke of Moſes: to wit, from the middle of the ſecond chapter of <hi>Geneſis</hi> vnto th' end of th' eleuenth: his ſtile is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with all maner of beauties and graces méete for a poeme, perfect and worthie to be honored of all men of good iudgement: ſo much of the worke in generall.<note place="margin">Foure books of the firſt day.</note> Now let vs ſée what the bookes of theſe two firſt daies containe in particular. After his méete prefaces and entrance proper to his matter, he placeth the firſt man in the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> painteth out the garden,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eden.</hi>
               </note> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth diuers queſtions commonly thereabout ariſing, as of the trée of life and th'excellencie therof, likewiſe of the trée of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and euill; and here he ſheweth what was the knowledge of man before ſinne, wherefore he was placed in Paradiſe, what was his exerciſe there, what was his happines before the fall: as namely, that he had familiar communication with God: whereunto is properly adioyned the diſcourſe of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11268:6"/>
traunces, and Reuelations: this done he toucheth the commandement of GOD to Adam concerning the forbidden fruit, the promiſe of our firſt father, the great pleaſures he enioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo long as he continued obedient: &amp; vpon this occaſion he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth poynt deuiſe the beauties of this garden: yet with ſuch a ſtay of himſelfe, that he cutteth off many curious demaunds, and hauing anſwered certaine obiections, endeth his firſt booke. In the beginning of the ſecond he ſetteth downe th' enuie and drift of the diuel againſt man,<note place="margin">2. <hi>L'imposture.</hi>
               </note> why he tempted outwardly, what moued him to take a body rather than preſent himſelfe: the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of a ſerpent, rather than to change himſelfe into an Angell of light. Hereout are handled opinions diuers, the concluſion of all is this: that the ſerpent was the diuels inſtrument to miſleade our firſt mother. This draweth the Poet to ſpeake of the power of Satan. So he returning to his former intent, diſcouereth all the wiles and aſſaults of th' enimie: how he brought Eue to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and Adam by meanes of hir: whence haue enſued effects moſt gréeuous to behold. Theſe miſerable ſinners exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, charged with ſinne, and condemned therefore, as well by remorſe of their owne conſcience, as by the fearful voice of their creator, who pronounceth doome againſt the ſerpent and them. Wherunto is added a ſound and full anſwere to all ſuch wicked and profane ſpirits as murmur againſt the fall of Man, as it is ſet downe in holy ſcripture: to ſhut vp the booke, Adam and Eue are chaſed out of Paradiſe, and an Angell with a firie ſword there placed to kéepe them out. Now the better to ſet forth the miſerie of man,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Furies.</hi>
               </note> and the confuſions which ſinne hath brought in among vs, the Poet hauing in the beginning of his third booke mentioned againe, and ſet before our eies the bleſſed eſtate of the whole world, and the perfect vnion that was among all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before the backſliding of Adam, the cauſe (as he ſheweth by diuers examples) of all their diſunion, he muſtereth and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth forth an armie of all other creatures to war againſt man: then comming to the euils that afflict this poore guiltie creature both within and without, he bringeth in the furies called out of hell to come and torment mankind. Theſe then are the plagues wherewith they chaſtiſe the bodie: to wit, famine, war, infinite
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11268:6"/>
ſort of diſeaſes, whereof the chiefe are named and ranged into foure ſquadrons: The firſt laieth ſiege to the head: the ſecond en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countreth the chiefe inſtruments of life: the third aſſaulteth the naturall powers: the fourth ſetteth on the outward parts of Man. They are diſtinguiſhed againe into maladies particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belonging vnto certaine peoples and climats, proper to the ſeuerall ages of man, ſpeciall to diuers ſeaſons of the yéere, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious, hereditarie, new, obſtinate, and vncurable. To increaſe the more this heape of miſerie, he proueth that beaſts are in this regard in better caſe than man. Then entreth into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the moſt dangerous diſeaſes of all, which are thoſe of the mind: and namely foure principall kindes, which vnder them containe all other, ſadnes, ioy, feare, and fond deſire: theſe with their traine and effects, are without compariſon more to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red than all the moſt cruell diſeaſes of the body, as by fit exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples is proued: and ſo the Poet concludeth with an holy wiſh and profitable exhortation to the Frenchmen.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Artifices.</hi>
               </note> Hereupon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the entrie of the fourth booke ſaluted peace, and ſhewed the commodities thereof, he falleth fitly to his purpoſe, and deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vnto vs the miſerable eſtate of Adam and Eue, being now foorth of the garden, what hard ſhift they made to liue, whereon they fed, how they were clothed, and what paines Eue tooke to weaue a garment for hir huſband: their furniture againſt the cold, their place of abode and firſt buildings, the inuention of fire, the beginning of houſholds, and how the land was peopled: the exerciſe of Caine and Abel, their ſacrifices, the wicked mind of Caine, who ſlue his brother, and after thinking ſomewhat to eaſe his ſoule of the gnawing torments of conſcience, built a towne, and began to ride horſes; which the Poet handleth in kinde, and from thence falleth into diſcourſe of th' inuention and vſe of Iron and inſtruments of Muſick. But as Caine and his followers buſie themſelues with affaires of the worlde, meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while Adam and his true children take after godlines and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and ſearch out the ſacrets of nature. Among other Seth is ſuppoſed to aſke his father concerning th' eſtate of the worlde from the beginning vnto th' end, which Adam, excuſing himſelf, at firſt refuſeth to do, but ſuddenly mooued with the holie ſpirit
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11268:7"/>
(héere diſtinguiſhed from the furies of men poſſeſſed of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell) he ſpeaketh of all the worlds ages, and ſheweth what ſhall befall euen to the flood: the diſcourſe and conſideration whereof ouercommeth his hart with griefe, depriueth him of ſpéech, and endeth the fourth booke, and ſo by conſequent the firſt daies hiſtorie.<note place="margin">Foure bookes of the ſecond day. 1. <hi>L' Arche.</hi>
               </note> Beginning the firſt booke of the ſecond day with a new inuocation, he entreth into th' Arch, recounteth the holie exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Noe, which <hi>Cham</hi> gainſaieth, and diuers waies ſtriueth againſt the prouidence of God: but Noe with many liuely and forcible arguments withſtandeth him: meanewhile the flood is abated, the Arch ſtaied, the Rauen and the Doue are ſent foorth, Noe commeth out of the Arch, the meaſure and burden whereof is in a few words plainly prooued. Then this good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch hauing ſacrificed, receiueth diuers lawes and promiſes of God, eſpecially that there ſhall be neuer more any vniuerſall flood, for token whereof the Rainbow is ordained: then Noe betaketh himſelfe to till the earth, planteth a vine, is droonke with the wine thereof, and ſléepeth on the ground in a ſhamefull maner, <hi>Cham</hi> maketh a ieſt of it, but Sem and Iaphet couer modeſtly the ſhame of their father, who now awakened out of his dronkennes, and much grieued thereat, curſeth <hi>Cham</hi> &amp; his poſteritie:<note place="margin">2. BABILON</note> ſo the Poet endeth his firſt booke. <hi>And to make way to the life of Nimrod he beginneth the ſecond, with conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the peoples happines that are gouerned by good &amp; wiſe princes, and the bad eſtate of ſuch as are ſlaues to ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, beſeeching God to withhold from vs ſuch confuſions as he liuely painteth out, in the diſcouering of Nimrods poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, who from his childhood ſetteth himſelfe a worke to get the ſoueraigntie ouer men, ſheweth his naturall bent among his play-fellowes, and for that behoofe ſpareth not his owne bodie: he beginneth to deale with wilde beaſtes, and maſtereth ſome particulars, by reaſon whereof he win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the peoples harts and is made gouernour: then he laieth himſelfe open; and to maintaine his tyrannie, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth into the peoples heads to build a towne and a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie tower, to withſtand the force of another Deluge: This ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth ſo good liking with the people, that they preſently ſet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11268:7"/>
themſelues on worke. But the Lord, prouoked to anger with their bold attempt, confoundeth the language of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſo as they are conſtrained to let all alone, not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding one another by reaſon of their different ſpeech, the roote of many inconueniences, whoſe contrarie commodities are declared: and ſo the Poet falleth into diſcourſe of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of toongs, and of th'aduantage that herein mankind hath aboue all other creatures: and proueth by many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that the Hebrue toong is the moſt ancient, that it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by deſcent from Adam vnto Nimrod, and remained laſt in the familie of Heber. Concerning other toongs, parted as they are ſundrie waies, mention is made of their alterations, as alſo of their force and vigour, much relying vpon vſe, which hath brought the Hebrue, Greeke, and Latine into requeſt. Here the Poet breathing awhile, caſteth into a new treatiſe, where he faineth a viſion, and in the ſame the dwelling place and image of Eloquence repreſented vnto him, and about this image, the toongs: Hebrue, Greeke, Latine, Italian, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian, Dutch, Spaniſh, Engliſh, and French, togither with the names of certaine perſonages, that in ſome one of them haue excelled: and after due reuerence done vnto them, he cloſeth vp his viſion and booke withall.</hi> Then in his third booke,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Colonies.</hi>
               </note> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againe in hand the aſtoniſhed builders of Babel, after he hath giuen a reaſon why God would not haue them ſtay in the plaine of Sennaar, he leadeth the children of Sem towards the eaſt, of Cham to the ſouth, of Iaphet to the north and weſt: but he chooſeth rather to ſtay himſelfe, than enter into the dark cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Antiquitie, ſhewing how much they deceiue themſelues and others, who venter too far that way: then deſcribeth he the diuers remooues of ſundrie nations, as of the Bretons, Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards, Alans and Vandals: reckoneth the cauſes why they ſhifted their abode: and baulking the vnknowen iourneyes of ſome nations, treateth of the voyages of certaine warlike peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, chiefly of the Gothes, Lumbards and Gaules. There againe ſtaying, he ſaith, to be ſhort, that the poſteritie of Noes thrée children peopled the world, not all at once, but by little and little, and as it were yéere after yéere with increaſe of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11268:8"/>
children: which alſo was th'occaſion why the firſt Monarchie was planted in <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> néere to the plaine of Sennaar, rather than elſewhere in any countrey not ſo ſoone inhabited: ſo the Hebrues and other neighbour peoples haue had the Arts, riches and ornaments of delight, before thoſe of the north and weſt knew what the world meant. Herupon is noted, firſt how Sem in the eaſt, then how Iaphet in the weſt, and laſtly how <hi>Cham</hi> in the ſouth, repleniſhed the world with people: it reſted that he ſhould ſpeake of the new world diſcouered in our time: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame he ſheweth how ſo huge a countrey was firſt inhabited, why not ſo ſoone as other parts of the world, and whereby it appéereth to haue bin yet a long time poſſeſſed: he propoundeth here certaine of his owne coniectures touching the proceſſe of this new worlds inhabitants, nameth diuers parts, and reckoneth vp certaine wonders thereof: then anſwereth fitly to this obiection; How it could be that Noe and his children ſhould haue ſo much increaſed: and there taketh occaſion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the wonderfull works of God in the diuers temper and complexion of nations, ſhewing how the northren differ from the ſouthren people, and euen thoſe of Europe among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, eſpecially the French, Dutch, Italian, and Spaniſh. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſheweth why God would haue the children of Noe be ſo diſparkled ouer the face of the earth: which is compared vnto a great citie, where men haue much to do one with another: then refuteth he the godleſſe crew, prouing (to their confuſion) that whatſoeuer they ſuppoſe created in vaine, and to ſerue to no vſe, ſtandeth vs oftentimes in greateſt ſtead, as witnes the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the mountaines, and the ſea. But now being wéerie (as it were) with ſo long ſailing, he landeth in France, &amp; ſingeth ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the praiſe therof, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluding that it wanteth nothing ſaue only a ſound peace, which he craueth at the hands of him that is able to giue it.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Colonnies.</hi>
               </note> In the beginning of the fourth and laſt booke, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth on God againe, being to enter into diſcourſe of a new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hautie, and very hard to handle, to wit, the Mathematikes; and the better to performe his drift, he ſuppoſeth <hi>Phaleg</hi> to haue found two ancient pillers, and to aſke of his father Heber what they meane: whereunto Heber anſwereth, and openeth the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11268:8"/>
doore of one of them, and ſheweth his ſonne foure images there incloſed: the firſt of them is Arithmetike, ſet out in hir proper attire with numbers: the ſecond is Geometrie, with hir tooles, works, and excellent crafts, particularly ſet downe: the third is Aſtronomie, holding in hir right hand the Earth-globe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the land, the ſea, and the ten circles of heauen are painted: and in hir left hand the ſphere of heauen, bedecked with figures and images, noting forth all the principall ſtars that are ſéene betwixt the two Poles. In this place is yéelded a reaſon of the names that are giuen to the twelue ſignes of the <hi>Zodiacke,</hi> and Heber himſelfe is made to hold opinion that the chiefe ſtars of the globe, which he numbreth, containe many myſteries of the church: but, as he endeuoreth to proue the ſame, the Poet appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a notable correction; and ſo goeth on to diſcouer the ſecrets of Aſtronomie: an art ſprung from the Hebrues to the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, from them conueied to th' Egyptians, and ſo to the Gréeks, Arabians, Italians, and Almaines: to end that diſcourſe he praiſeth the learned Aſtronomers, and hauing declared the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of their ſkil, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to view the fourth image, which is Muſick: hir he liuely pourtraieth in all hir brauerie, declareth hir perfection, and what power ſhe hath ouer beaſts, foules, men of vnderſtanding, and God himſelfe: this done, as <hi>Heber</hi> was about to go forward, <hi>Canan</hi> breaketh of their talke, by occaſion whereof the Poet reſteth himſelfe, and ſo makes an end of the ſecond day of his ſecond wéeke.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11268:9"/>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:11268:9"/>
            <head>BABILON.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>O How great good it is to liue vnder a <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Prince,<note place="margin">A preface repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by good and wiſe princes, and the diſtreſſe of people ſubiect to a Tyrant. Fitly foreplaced of the Poet to lead him to the life and deedes of Nimrod.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That counts more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his weal, the weal of his ꝓuince!</l>
                     <l>Still hark'ning to the wiſe, no eare to gloſer lending,</l>
                     <l>The wicked puniſhing, and honeſt man defending:</l>
                     <l>That ſou'raigne of himſelfe, doth all vice ouer-awe,</l>
                     <l>More by his honeſt life, than puniſhment, or lawe:</l>
                     <l>That being inward meeke, outward maieſticall,</l>
                     <l>Hath, for his perſons guard, loue of his ſubiects all.</l>
                     <l>That makes no idol of his bright imperled Mace;</l>
                     <l>And knowing himſelfe ſet on ſtages higheſt place,</l>
                     <l>Where to controll his works, a world hath him in ſight,</l>
                     <l>Doth not what ere him liſt, but rather what is right.</l>
                     <l>But ſure a hell it is to liue in ſeruitude,</l>
                     <l>A mans whole courſe of life, vnder a <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Tyrant rude:</l>
                     <l>Such one as Dionyſe, that with hot coles him ſhau'd,</l>
                     <l>Or Nero, that his houſe with inceſt all deprau'd:</l>
                     <l>Or as an owle, that hates the light of gouernment,</l>
                     <l>Of parlament and peeres, that feares the prattlement</l>
                     <l>Of euery priuate toong, that for his beſt delight,</l>
                     <l>His ſubiects ſets at ods, and ſtill maintains their ſpight.</l>
                     <l>Ne're ſets before his eies faith, honour or iuſtice,</l>
                     <l>But raiſeth eurie day office vpon office:</l>
                     <l>Nor would his ſubiects were the beſt learn'd, wiſeſt, ſtrongeſt,</l>
                     <l>But eu'rie day crops off, that eare whoſe ſtalke is longeſt</l>
                     <l>Throughout his harueſt field: and worſe than Tigre wood,</l>
                     <l>Will not his kindred ſpare, no not his brothers blood.</l>
                     <l>Who though enuironed with ſword and halberds aid,</l>
                     <l>Yet feares much people, more than he doth make afraid:</l>
                     <l>Reioyceth to inuent, new taxes generall,</l>
                     <l>And his owne to the bones, eates like a Caniball.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Imprint (O king of heau'n) within our princes breſts,<note place="margin">A praier to God, fitly ariſing of the words and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aforegoing, and making way to the ſequele.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Loue to their people-ward, and reu'rence of thine heſts.</l>
                     <l>And incaſe any courtiers poyſoned language,</l>
                     <l>Or theſe enormities familiar in our age,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:11268:10"/>Shall leaue there any taint of Nimrods propertie,</l>
                     <l>Draw thereupon thy quill, and raſe it ſpeedily:</l>
                     <l>That for proud Babels towre they may thy Sion reare,</l>
                     <l>And my Muſe vnder them may chaunt it eu'ry where.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <div n="1" type="note">
                     <head>1.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prince.</hi> Here is the liuely image of a good Prince ſet downe vnto vs in a few lines, borrowed of a many good Auctors both diuine and humane, that teach in their writings rules and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples notable for this purpoſe. Moſes in the law, Dauid in the <hi>101.</hi> Pſalme, do declare vnto vs, the rules of dutie belonging vnto gouernours: and they themſelues, with all thoſe the good iudges and kings that were among the people of God, ſerue for ſure patternes and examples to all ſuch as meane faithfully to diſcharge the like duties. Alſo Plato, Ariſtotle, Xenophon, and Plutarch, with diuers others, for the inſtruction of thoſe that came after them, haue ſet foorth many godly precepts and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. The commodities that ariſe out of euery one of theſe vertues here deſcribed (each one whereof requireth a large com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie) are infinite: and where there are now adaies ſuch princes in the world, their ſubiects may thinke themſelues ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding happie. For next after the ſincere knowledge and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the true God, there is no greater happines in the world for vs to enioy, than to be gouerned by ſuch vertuous perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as are here deſcribed: marke then the perfect image of the good Prince.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="note">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tyrant.</hi> To giue the better gloſſe to the former picture, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cleane contrarie, and maruellous fearfull to behold, he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth here before our eyes the picture of a Tyrant that liueth in miſtruſt of the whole world, as did Dionyſius the elder tyrant of Sicilie, of whom we reade among the liues of Plutarch. He was ſo miſtruſtfull, that for feare of his barbers, he made his daughters bring him a burning cole to ſindge his haire withall. More than this, a Tyrant defileth himſelf with inceſts, whoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, adulteries, and the ſinne of Sodom, and therewith infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth his whole court and countrie: as that filthie Nero did, whoſe life is written by Suetonius, Tacitus, and others, reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting therein many horrible and ſhamefull caſes. Againe, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11268:10"/>
Tyrant will be ſubiect vnto no law, nor order whatſoeuer; he ouerthroweth the ground-lawes and pillers of the ſtate: or if he ſéeme willing to ſubmit himſelfe thereunto, it is to further himſelfe ſo much the more in the vndermyning, by diuers hid practiſes, and deſtroying all ſuch as might any way reſiſt, or make head againſt him. Hence commeth it to paſſe, that he may in no wiſe abide any inquiſition or examination to be made of his vnworthie and vile outrages, but vaunteth of the iniurie that priuate men ſuffer, and diſcredite they are driuen vnto by meanes of his oppreſſion. To maintaine his ſtate the better, he entertaineth and vpholdeth all maner of hurlyburlies, factions, quarrels, and ciuill wars: he fauoureth ruffians, bawdes, flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, liers, light and looſe perſons, murderers, impoyſoners, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, Atheiſts, and ſuch as are defiled with all maner of vice and wickednes. He promiſeth mountaines, performeth nothing: glorieth to breake oth and promiſe, and to deceiue and ſurpriſe both ſmall and great by faire words, ſwéete ſpéech, humble and curteous countenance, when his hart imagineth villanie and treaſon to his countrie. He neuer forbeareth any thing, neuer pardoneth any man, nouriſheth and fatteth himſelfe with blood and fire: all peaceable and vertuous perſons he diſgraceth and ouerthroweth, ſupporting and aduancing all peace-breakers, robbers, and wicked liuers: he taketh bribes for all offices, and oppreſſeth the people with the vnbrideled number of catchpole-officers, that maintaine themſelues onely by grating vpon others: his ſubiects he would haue liue all daies of their life in ignorance: painfull, wiſe, and learned men, and thoſe that haue well to take vnto, bicauſe they néede the leſſe to depend on him, or ſell themſelues for his fauour, he chaſeth far from him, and maketh beholding vnto him none but fooles, idiots, ieſters, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, wranglers, and ſuch copes-mates as of naught-worth are ſuddenly ſtart vp, that wholy depend vpon him, and reuell in his cofers, not giuing him (as they cannot) any good counſell for the commonwealth; they care not which end thereof go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: but all their care and counſell is for their priuate gaine, which ſerues to no better vſe, than to intice and draw them on daily to careleſſe and wicked liuing. Further yet, ſo far is he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11268:11"/>
from regarding or placing néere about him men of worth and good qualities, that on the contrary, to the imitation of Tarqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, ſurnamed the proud (whoſe ſtorie Liuie writeth in the firſt booke of his ſecond Decade, concerning the Poppie heads that he broke downe with his ſtaffe, to teach his ſonne by a domb ſhew, that he ſhould rid out of the way al the péeres of the citie, and forſake (as another ſaith) fifty frogs to catch one Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) he breaketh downe the higheſt eares of corne: that is, he cauſeth al thoſe to be put to death, that might any wayes hinder his wicked intents. What ſhould I ſay more? Such a curſed creature, without God, without conſcience, woorſe than any wilde beaſt, ſpareth neither kiffe nor kin, but either by ſword or poiſon maketh away the very néereſt of all his blood, that he may raigne alone, if it were poſſible. But notwithſtanding the many bands of his guard, he ſtandeth in feare of euery man, and is deſpiſed, mocked, and deteſted of all. For why? Beſides that is aforeſaid, he glorieth and taketh delight to deuiſe new ſubſidies, impoſts, and tributes, whereby the comminaltie may be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueriſhed, and held in bondage, and ſo in ſtéede of Homers people-féeder, he becommeth a people-eater. Of this image of a Tyrant, there are examples aboue number found, both in ancient &amp; late writers of Church hiſtories, and others: So I returne to the Poet.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Nimrods firſt ſtudie and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, to get the ſoueraigntie of the people, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note>3. <hi>Nimrod</hi> ſcarce yet in age to twelue yeeres did ariſe,</l>
                     <l>But ouer all his peeres, he ſets to tyranniſe:</l>
                     <l>He ouergrowes them all, and of his might future,</l>
                     <l>The ground-worke planteth he vpon ſo good Augure:</l>
                     <l>And bearing in his hand, in ſteed of ſcepters reedes,</l>
                     <l>Among the ſhepheard-ſwaines begins his prentiſe-deedes.</l>
                     <l>Then knowing that the man, whoſe courage doth aſpire,</l>
                     <l>Vnto the deemed bliſſe of an awfull empire,</l>
                     <l>Muſt paſſe in braue exploits the doltiſh vulgar ſort,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe by ſeeming good, obtaine a good report:</l>
                     <l>He paſſed not the night drown'd in a feather bed,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet the day in ſhade: but yoong accuſtomed</l>
                     <l>Himſelfe to good and ill, making ambitiouſly</l>
                     <l>His boulſter of a rocke, his curtaines of the skie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:11268:11"/>Sweate is his ſweet delight, his games are bow and arrowes,</l>
                     <l>His Ganimeads the liſts, his haukes the little ſparrowes.</l>
                     <l>His moſt delicious meat, the fleſh of tender kid,</l>
                     <l>Which trembleth yet, and ſcarce is from the skin vnhid.</l>
                     <l>Somtime he ſports himſelfe, to conquer with one breth,<note place="margin">The continuance of his labours to obtaine the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples fauour.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Some craggie rocks aſſcent that ouer-peeres the heath:</l>
                     <l>Or elſe ſome raging flood, againſt the ſtreame diuide,</l>
                     <l>That ſwolne with raine, hath drou'n a hundred brigs aſide,</l>
                     <l>And with a bounding courſe, vnbrid'led gallops faſt,</l>
                     <l>All ouerthwart the ſtones, in ſome ſtrait vallie caſt:</l>
                     <l>Or elſe after his caſt, to catch againe his dart,</l>
                     <l>Or in plaine field on foote, to take the Hinde or Hart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But now once ouerpaſt twenty fiue yeeres of age,</l>
                     <l>And feeling with high minde, his ſinewes and courage</l>
                     <l>Worthie a fiercer Mars, if he know any where</l>
                     <l>A Lion, a Leopard, a Tigre, or a Beare,</l>
                     <l>He fearleſſe ſets thereon, kils, conquereth, and foiles,</l>
                     <l>And plants in higheſt place of thoſe the bloodie ſpoiles.</l>
                     <l>The people then that ſee, by his hands martiall frayes,</l>
                     <l>From thoſe boot-hailers wilde, each-where ſet free the wayes,</l>
                     <l>The fearfull cattels heardes, and all the waſte foreſts</l>
                     <l>Rid of their hideous cries, loues this tamer of beaſts,</l>
                     <l>This chaſe-ill Hercules, and ſhewes him ſpeciall fauour,</l>
                     <l>And cals him euermore their father and their ſauiour.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nimrod now by the haire hand-faſting this good fortune,<note place="margin">He leaueth his former chaſe for a better pray.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſtriking th' iron hot, doth flatter, preſſe, importune,</l>
                     <l>Somtime ſome, ſomtime others, and haſting to his bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>Before that hunted beaſts, now of men hunter is.</l>
                     <l>For as he did imploy, in his hunting before,</l>
                     <l>The grins, hare-pipes, and traps, and all the limie ſtore:</l>
                     <l>And further at his need, againſt the moſt haggarts,</l>
                     <l>The heauie clubs, the ſhafts, the ſharpe ſwords, and the darts:</l>
                     <l>So ſome mens harts he gaines, by faire hopes cloſely ſtealing,</l>
                     <l>Others he wins by gifts, and others by hard dealing,</l>
                     <l>And breaking furiouſly the bonds of equitie,</l>
                     <l>Of that reſpringing world, vſurpes the Royaltie.</l>
                     <l>Whereas in time before the chiefe of each houſhold</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:11268:12"/>The ſame did rule apart, nor did the yoong-man bold,</l>
                     <l>Boyſt'rous, ambitious, vpon a wanton braue,</l>
                     <l>His ſickle thruſt (as now) in harueſt of the graue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <div n="3" type="note">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nimrod ſcarce yet.</hi> The poſteritie of Noe being much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, as Moſes reckoneth in the 10. chapter of Geneſis, they began to ſpread abroad and take ſeuerall habitations, but not farre one from another ſo ſoone after the flood. Among other the ſonnes of <hi>Cham,</hi> is numbred <hi>Cus</hi> the father of <hi>Nimrod,</hi> of whom the hiſtorie maketh mention, that he began to be great on the earth, and was a mightie hunter before the almightie, and that the beginning of his raigne was <hi>Babel, Erech, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chad,</hi> and <hi>Calneh,</hi> in the land of Sennaar. Vpon this place are giuen two diuers expoſitions: The firſt is, of ſome that hold that <hi>Nimrod</hi> was the firſt after the flood that gaue any méete fourme of publike gouernment, and by the conſent of many families, conſidering his wiſedome and valour, was accepted for maiſter and gouernour, to rule and order many houſholds togither: by reaſon whereof, (ſay they) he is called a ſtrong hunter before the Lord: and namely, for that he repreſſed, by maine force, the wicked and vnruly, who, like ſauage beaſts, praied vpon the life of man. But the greater part of Expoſitors take this other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and hold, that <hi>Nimrod</hi> by force and diuers ſubtilties (here finely ſet downe by the Poet) got the ſupremacie; and that this power aſcribed vnto him, was not truely Royall and lawfull, but a power vſurped by force, a hunters power, wherewith he ſurpriſed men, and raigning ouer them cruelly, handled them as if they were beaſts, yea, and that before the Lord, which is as much to ſay, as in deſpite of God, who had eſtabliſhed a gentle rule and gouernment among the families. This ſecond expoſition is the more certaine; whether we conſider the race of <hi>Nimrod,</hi> or the proper meaning and ſequele of the words of the text, or the buildings of <hi>Nimrod,</hi> or what ſucceſſe his proud attempt had. The Poet relying on this opinion, hath further followed in the deſcription of the youth, and exerciſes of this firſt Tyrant that was in the ſecond world, ſuch things as were likely to be, and that with ſuch a grace, as in a diſcourſe is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11268:12"/>
that out of the holie Scripture hath ſo narrow foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in other bookes is, with many fables and names vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, darkened.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">4</hi> Now he enthroned is,<note place="margin">The tyrannous gouerment of Nimrod, and his proud attempt.</note> by force he will haue wrought</l>
                     <l>A thouſand cruelties, careleſſely ſets at naught</l>
                     <l>Lawes both of God and man, out-braues th'almightie king,</l>
                     <l>And reares vp to his noſe the ſcepter floriſhing.</l>
                     <l>And leaſt the people at length (eaſe puffing vp their pride)</l>
                     <l>Should thinke to caſt his yoke, he keeps them occupide.</l>
                     <l>He powreth foorth his coyne, and makes them labour ſtill,</l>
                     <l>In building of a Towre, more like an Atlas hill.</l>
                     <l>We liue too long (quoth he) thus like beaſts wandering:</l>
                     <l>Let's leaue theſe gadding tents, theſe houſes wayfaring:</l>
                     <l>A pallace let vs build, that ſtately may be ioynt,</l>
                     <l>In Baſe vnto the deepe, and vnto heau'n in Poynt.</l>
                     <l>A Sanctuarie ſafe, and priuiledg'd refuge,</l>
                     <l>Againſt the ſwelling rage of a rauenous Deluge.</l>
                     <l>Come let vs build a Towne, and there incorporate,</l>
                     <l>Paſſe the reſt of our daies vnder a royall ſtate:</l>
                     <l>Leaſt that we ſundered in tents with many princes,</l>
                     <l>Be ſcattered abroad throughout all the prouinces,</l>
                     <l>That with bright ſhining courſe are viewd by Phoebes brother,</l>
                     <l>Not able then to helpe, or counſell one another:</l>
                     <l>And in caſe burning coles of at-home-breed ſedition,</l>
                     <l>Or what miſhap ſo e're, ſhall driue vs to diuiſion,</l>
                     <l>Yet brothers, let vs leaue for laſting monument</l>
                     <l>Our names grau'n on theſe wals, high as the firmament.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">5</hi> Like as the Vulcan weake, that ſome chill companie,<note place="margin">A fit compariſon to ſhew what force haue the plots of tyrants, to bring the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God vpon the people.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of ſhepheards in the leaffie verges haue let lie</l>
                     <l>Of ſome one foreſt wide, a while it ſelfe keepes in,</l>
                     <l>Yet vomiting ſmoke-waues, dark'neth the bright welkin:</l>
                     <l>Then by ſoft Zephyrs helpe, whiles in low buſh it lurks,</l>
                     <l>Makes a red flaming way to his fierce angers works;</l>
                     <l>Vp to the blooming Thorne, fro th' humble buſh it ſtirs,</l>
                     <l>From thorne to oke, from oke vp to the talleſt firs,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill it gaineth ground, by running force it findes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11268:13"/>No Dryades it leaues within their natiue rindes:</l>
                     <l>Right ſo this pleaſant ſpeech ſoone as his toong had plac'd,</l>
                     <l>Of ſome few Fauorites with praiſe it was imbrac'd:</l>
                     <l>And ſtraight with giddie-braines it goes from hand to hand,</l>
                     <l>Eu'n to the baſer ſort of people through the land,</l>
                     <l>Who greatly bent to ſee the great Towre perfect made,</l>
                     <l>Themſelues toyle day and night, eu'ry chone in his trade.</l>
                     <l>Some trip great Asſhes downe, with ſharp-edg'd axes ſtrokes,</l>
                     <l>Some fell the ſailing Elmes, and ſome th'enduring okes.</l>
                     <l>So they degrade the woods, and ſhew vnto the Sunne</l>
                     <l>The ground where his bright eye before had neuer ſhunne.</l>
                     <l>Haſt thou at any time, an armie ſeene to ſacke</l>
                     <l>A citie vanquiſhed? ther's griefe and ioy no lacke,</l>
                     <l>Togither hurly burl'd, one carteth, one takes hold,</l>
                     <l>One drawes, another leades, and there the ſoldiour bold</l>
                     <l>Can finde no place too ſure, nor yet no locke too ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>The whole towne in one day forth at the gates doth throng:</l>
                     <l>So do theſe carpenters pill off in one moment,</l>
                     <l>From thoſe Aſſyrian hils, the ſhaking ornament</l>
                     <l>Of their ſhadie Deſerts, deſpoyle they the mountains,</l>
                     <l>And boiling hot mow down the trembling branched plains.</l>
                     <l>The waines and teemes of Mules, ſcarce one by other wend:</l>
                     <l>The groning axeltrees, o'rcharg'd with loades do bend.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">A liuely deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a people buſied about a great worke.</note>Heere to make morter hard, one day and night is bruing,</l>
                     <l>Of ſome thicke ſlimy poole the water flatly gluing:</l>
                     <l>Heere the brick-burner bakes within his ſmokie kell</l>
                     <l>Claie into ſtone, and heere ſome hollow downe to hell</l>
                     <l>So deepe foundations, that many a damned ſpright</l>
                     <l>Gazeth on once againe the ſunnes vnhoped light.</l>
                     <l>All heau'n replyes the ſound of their maules clitter clatters,</l>
                     <l>And Tigris feeles his fiſh all trembling vnd'r his waters.</l>
                     <l>The ruddie coloured wals in length and height do growe,</l>
                     <l>Far do they caſt a ſhade, far do they make a ſhowe.</l>
                     <l>With workmen al's turmoyl'd, the feeble and mortall frie,</l>
                     <l>Thinke at the firſt daies work, their hand ſhall reach the skie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">God being angry with the bould enterpriſe of Nimrod and his followers, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth to breake of their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, by confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">6</hi> God ſeeing this, to wrath inclin'd his countenance,</l>
                     <l>And with a thundring ſound, that doth like tempeſt glance,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:11268:13"/>Downe through the clowdy plain, that doth hils ouerthrow,</l>
                     <l>And makes heau'ns ſtedfaſt gates flaſh often too and fro,</l>
                     <l>See, ſee (quoth he) theſe dwarfes, ſee this ſame raſcall people!</l>
                     <l>Theſe children of the duſt, O what a goodly ſteeple,</l>
                     <l>What mightie wals they build! O th'impregnable caſtle,</l>
                     <l>Of ſtrength to beare my ſhot, and with my wroth to wraſtle!</l>
                     <l>I ſware an oth to them, hencefoorth the fruitfull ground</l>
                     <l>Should neuer ſtand in feare of waters breaking bound:</l>
                     <l>They doubting, ſenſe themſelues: I would by their extent</l>
                     <l>Haue peopled all the world, they by themſelues here pent</l>
                     <l>Are priſner-like emparkt: I would haue bin for euer</l>
                     <l>Their maſter, their defence, their ſhepheard, their law-giuer;</l>
                     <l>And they haue choſe for king a ſauage liue-by-ſpoyle,</l>
                     <l>A tyrant ſeeking gaine by their great loſſe and toyle:</l>
                     <l>Who doth my force deſpiſe, and with vaine-glorie ſwo'ne,</l>
                     <l>Attempts to ſcale the wals, of my moſt holy throne.</l>
                     <l>Come, let's breake off their drift, and ſith by ſpeeches vnitie,</l>
                     <l>As by will, as by law, and as by conſanguinitie,</l>
                     <l>They hart'ned are to ill, and with a ſaucie toong,</l>
                     <l>Waxe mad vpon this worke all night and all day long;</l>
                     <l>Let's ſet a pulbacke on their haſtie-pac'd intention,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrike them quickly with the ſpirit of diſſention.</l>
                     <l>Their language let's confound, and make both one and other,</l>
                     <l>Sire barbarous to his ſonne, and brother deafe to brother.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">7</hi> Thus had he ſaid, and ſtraight confuſedly there went</l>
                     <l>I know not what a noiſe throughout the battlement.<note place="margin">The execution of Gods ſentence.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Right ſuch a iangling ſound as one heares in a band</l>
                     <l>Of ſlaues, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drunkards God doth with his launce co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand.</l>
                     <l>One doth his language toothe, another noze his note,</l>
                     <l>Another frames his words vnſeemly through the throte,</l>
                     <l>One howles, and one doth hiſſe, another ſluttereth;</l>
                     <l>Each hath his babble, and each in vaine endeuoreth</l>
                     <l>To find thoſe loued termes thoſe tunes before expreſt,</l>
                     <l>That in their rowling cradle they drew from mothers breſt.</l>
                     <l>Go get thee vp betimes,<note place="margin">A fit compariſon.</note> and whiles the morning gay</l>
                     <l>With Rainbow-gloſſe bedecks the portail of the day,</l>
                     <l>Giue eare awhile and marke the diſagreeing moodes</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:11268:14"/>Of thoſe trim quiriſters that ſing amidſt the woodes</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Goodmorrow to their loues:</hi> where each one in his faſhion,</l>
                     <l>Pearched vpon a bough, pronounceth his oration:</l>
                     <l>Then ſhalt thou vnderſtand what mingle-mangle of ſounds</l>
                     <l>Confuſedly was heard among thoſe maſon-lounds:</l>
                     <l>A Trowell ho ſaith one, his mate a Beetle heaues;</l>
                     <l>Cut me ſaith he this ſtone, and he ſome timber cleaues;</l>
                     <l>Come ho, come ho, ſaith one, and winde me vp this rope:</l>
                     <l>Then one vnwinding ſtriues to giue it all the ſcope;</l>
                     <l>This ſcaffold bourd, ſaith one, one makes it downe too fare:</l>
                     <l>Giue me the line ſaith one, and one giues him the ſquare.</l>
                     <l>He ſhoutes, he ſignes in vaine, and he with anger boyles,</l>
                     <l>And looke what one hath made, forthwith another ſpoyles.</l>
                     <l>With thoſe confuſed cries they windles chafe in vaine:</l>
                     <l>Each one the more he ſtriues the leſſe appeeres his paine.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Another excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent compariſon declaring how neither counſell, art, force, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, nor mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, is able to reſiſt God.</note>And ſhortly as the men that altogither ſtood</l>
                     <l>To build in channell deepe of ſome great rau'ning flood</l>
                     <l>High arches of a bridge, marking from hils deſcend</l>
                     <l>A hundred ſudden ſtreames, and now far to extend</l>
                     <l>The mountaine-hating waues, leaue off without aduiſe,</l>
                     <l>Scudding ſome here, ſome there, their goodly enterpriſe:</l>
                     <l>Right ſo theſe Architects, feeling the ſtormie ſmart</l>
                     <l>Of Gods diſpleaſure riſe, had neither ſtrength nor hart.</l>
                     <l>But there they left their worke, and with hands malcontent,</l>
                     <l>Rules, mallets, plummets, lines, all down the Towre they ſent.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <div n="4" type="note">
                     <head>4.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Now he enthroned is.</hi> This is the expoſition of the words, <hi>mighty hunter before the Lord:</hi> to wit, that Nimrod Chams nephew, did proudly lift himſelfe vp againſt God and man. His buildings and the beginning of his raigne could not haue béene ſuch, without offring violence to the peace and libertie of diuers families ouer whom he bare rule: and there is no ſhew to the contrarie, but that by diuers practiſes from time to time he got the ſoueraigntie. The holy Scripture oftentimes by the names of hunters and chaſers, meaneth Gods enimies, and the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of his church. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 91. <hi>&amp;</hi> 124. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 32. <hi>Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> 3. The ſeauentie Interpreters tranſlate th' Hebrue text
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11268:14"/>
after this maner: This Nimrod began to be a Gyant on the earth, and a hunteſman, or leader of houndes before the Lorde God. By the hounds of Nimrod may be vnderſtood his guardes, and the fauorers of his tyrannie. Moſes calleth him <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor tſaid,</hi> that is, luſty, ſtrong, or great and mightie chaſer. Which noteth not onely the ſtature and height of bodie, but alſo might and authoritie ioyned with violence, in all thoſe that want the feare of God. Now although Moſes in the 11. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> where he ſpeaketh of the citie &amp; towre of Babel, make no mention of Nimrod, yet hath the Poet aptly gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the chapter aforegoing, that Nimrod was the author and promoter of thoſe buildings; in as much as Babel is called the beginning of his raigne, who could not any waies raigne without ſome habitations for himſelfe and his ſubiects, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that Moſes in the ſelfe ſame place affirmeth, that the cities founded by Nimrod were in the countrey of Sennaar, and that in the 12. verſe of the 11. chapter he ſaith, that theſe builders of Babel dwelt on a plaine in the countrey of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naar: by good reaſon the inuention and beginning thereof is héere aſcribed to Nimrod, who by this meanes ſought to ſet his ſtate on foote. Alſo this Monarchie of Babylon, was one of the firſt, and with it that of Niniuie, as may be gathered out of the wordes of Moſes. But the more particular diſcourſe of theſe matters, and diuerſe other queſtions concerning Nimrod and his outrages, require a larger commentarie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="note">
                     <head>5.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Like as the Vulcan weake.</hi> The Poet ſaith, that as a ſmall deale of fire let fall by ſome ſhepheards among the drie leaues of a great foreſt, ſetting it ſelfe, and hatching (as it were) the heate awhile, at length with helpe of the winde, groweth to ſo great a flame, that it taketh the whole foreſt, and leaueth not a <hi>Driad,</hi> that is, not a trée in his proper or naturall barke: So the words firſt vttered by Nimrod, the blowne with the bellowes of his mynions &amp; fauorites, ſet ſo the harts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on fire, that he ſoon obtained his purpoſe. This is it that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes noteth in the 11. chap. of <hi>Gen.</hi> the 3. and 4. verſ. They ſaide one to another (the chiefe men hauing put it in their heads) Come, let vs make bricke, and burne it well in the fire: ſo had
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11268:15"/>
they bricke inſtéed of ſtone, and ſlime had they in ſteade of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Then ſaid they, go let vs build vs a citie, and a tower, whoſe top may reach vnto the heauens, that we may get vs a name, leaſt we be ſcattered vpon the whole earth. The Poet in his verſe diſcourſeth vpon this deuiſe. It is thought that this proud building was begun about a hundred and fiftie yéeres after the flood. The good patriarch Noe, that liued yet long time after, ſaw his poſteritie confounded and ſcattered: for ſo it was the Lords will to exerciſe the patient faith of his ſeruant, to whom in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence he ſhewed the effect of his bleſſings in the familie of Sem, where ſtill remained the Hebrue toong, togither with the doctrine and diſcipline of the true church. Now out of this hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Moſes touching the building of the towne, and the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the builders, is ſprong (as it ſéemeth) the fabulous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Poets, ſet downe by Quid in his firſt booke of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſis,</hi> touching the Gyants that heaped hils one vpon another to ſcale heauen, and diſpoſſeſſe Iupiter of his throne. Thus hath Satan endeuoured to falſifie the truth of ſacred hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories. Well, this arrogant building ſheweth vs how vaine are the imaginations of worldly men, namely, to ſet at naught the true renowme of heauenly life, and ſéeke after the falſe on earth. Carnall men haue no care at all to worſhip and reuerence the name of the true God, they regarde onely to be accounted of themſelues, and ſo to write their names in the duſt. Againſt th' attempts of the men of Babel, and all their ſucceſſors, let vs oppoſe theſe ſentences, the <hi>18.</hi> and <hi>21.</hi> of <hi>Prouerbs.</hi> The name of the Lord is a ſtrong towre, thither ſhall the iuſt repaire and be exalted. There is no wiſedome, nor vnderſtanding, nor force, can preuaile againſt the Lord: and that which is written Pſal. the <hi>127.</hi> Except the Lord do buylde the houſe, the builders la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour but in vaine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="note">
                     <head>6.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>God ſeeing this:</hi> Moſes in the <hi>5.</hi> and <hi>6.</hi> verſes of the <hi>11.</hi> chapter ſaith: Then the Lord came downe to ſée the citie, and Towre, which the ſonnes of men had built. And the Lorde ſaide, Behold the people is one, and they all haue one language, and this they begin to do, neither can they now be ſtopped from whatſoeuer they haue imagined to do: come on, let vs go
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:11268:15"/>
downe and there confound their language, that they vnderſtand not one another. Then he addeth the execution of the ſentence, ſaying; So the Lorde ſcattered them from thence vpon all the earth, and they left off to build the citie. Therefore the name of it was called Babel, bicauſe the Lord did there confounde the language of all the earth, and ſcattered them from thence ouer all the world. God, that is all in all, neuer changeth his place, he goeth neither vpwarde nor downwarde, but the Scripture ſaith, he goeth downe then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he worketh any thing on earth, which falling out beyond and againſt the ordinarie courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, witneſſeth his particular preſence. Vnder theſe few words of Moſes, a many things are to be conſidered: chiefly, he noteth the great ſinnes of the builders, in that he bringeth in the Lord, iudge of the whole world, vouchſaufing to bow downe his eies particularly vpon that fooliſh people. For it is not without cauſe that the great God of heauen and earth ſhoulde ariſe from his throne, and (if I durſt ſo ſay) leaue the palace of his glorie to come and view the durt-dawbers or morter-makers. By this manner of ſpéech Moſes ſheweth, and giueth vs to vnderſtand, that long time before theſe Babylonians had built in their harts moſt woonderfull high and ſtately towers, and that long ago they had bak'd in the fire of their concupiſcence ſome mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous brickes: to wit, they had much counſailed one with an other, and diſcourſed of meanes to get renowme, and found no better way to attaine their purpoſe, than to raiſe a tower vp to the heauens, to rauiſh with aſtoniſhment all thoſe that ſhoulde beholde it. So Moſes ſaith that this pride and frowarde ſelfe-truſt deſerued a gréeuous puniſhment: but as God is parfaitly iuſt, ſo layeth he vpon the builders a chaſtiſement proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto their offence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="note">
                     <head>7.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thus had he ſaid and ſtraight.</hi> In God it is all one to will and to do: And further, he ſendeth not lightning, winde, nor tempeſt againſt the tower: but contenteth himſelf to ſtrike the proud and puffed vp braines of the builders: and ſo the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding founded vpon their follie was ouerthrowne by their fooliſh iangling that God mingled with their language; and the vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious maſons in ſtéed of their imagined renowme, haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:11268:16"/>
themſelues euerlaſting ſhame. Who would haue thought that God had had ſo readie ſuch kinde of rods to puniſh mankinde withall? But let the Reader conſider whether the world at this day be not full of Babel-towers. Marke what a number of men do in euery kind of vocation. Sith I do not take vpon me but to write bare Annotations, I leaue it to the Readers conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who may ſée, now more then euer, that the world continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the building of Babel: that is, men madly gainſet their owne wiſedome and power againſt the wiſedome and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God; who treading as it were with woollen féete, and ſtealing on ſoftly, is able with an arme of Iron to ſurpriſe and ſeize vpon theſe builders, and turne by diuers means their vaine purpoſes and weake endeuours to naught. The Poet hath vſed many verie fit compariſons to repreſent the confuſion of theſe workmen. The firſt is taken from that which we ſée fall out in a great rabblement of Peſants, ouerruled by the Launce or Mace of <hi>Bacchus:</hi> that is, ſuch as haue the Wine in their heads, and are dronken: for among ſuch people is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly heard a ſtrange confuſed noiſe &amp; iangling, as the Churh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ales and Wakes, and other ſuch paſſe-times do now and then declare. The ſecond is taken from the chirping of Birdes, in voice and ſong diuers. The third from Maſons, conſtrained by the ſodaine rage of a land-flood, to leaue off the begun worke of a Bridge. And héere is a liuely deſcription of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, togither with their degrées and conſequences: namely, in the confuſion of vnderſtandings firſt, then of ſpéech, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the whole company; which being vnable longer to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, was quickly ſo ſcattered, that (as Moſes ſaith) they ceaſſed to builde the Citie.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The harmes that men ſuffer by the confuſion of ſpeech.</note>O proud rebellion, O traiterous impietie!</l>
                     <l>Marke in what maner ſort by thy ſpeeches varietie</l>
                     <l>God hath thee puniſhed, alas that pleaſant toong,</l>
                     <l>That holy bond of townes, of anger bridle ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>Strong glue of amitie, once one, now doth wayfare</l>
                     <l>In hundred riuers drie; this gould ſo richly rare,</l>
                     <l>Wroth-taming, charming-care, men-drawing, hart-inta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gling,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:11268:16"/>Both colour, waight, and ſound, hath loſt by mingle-mangling.</l>
                     <l>This gift corrupted is, and from the North to South</l>
                     <l>Babels confuſed fall ſounds yet in eu'ry mouth.</l>
                     <l>The cold Finlanders once might viſit Africans,</l>
                     <l>The Spaniſh Indians, th' Engliſh Americans,</l>
                     <l>Without interpreters; but now the compas ſmall</l>
                     <l>That doth our cities bound, our language bounds withall:</l>
                     <l>And if we from our home but ne're ſo little went,</l>
                     <l>Dombe ſhould we be, and reſt of reaſons inſtrument.</l>
                     <l>Or if we ſpeake at leaſt vnto our neybour nations,</l>
                     <l>Tis by a borrow'd toong, or by ſtrange animations.</l>
                     <l>Without ſchoole, without paines, ſucking our mothers breſt,</l>
                     <l>We might haue learn'd the tong that all mens minds expreſt;</l>
                     <l>And after ſeu'n yeeres old, vpon ſmall gliſtring ſand</l>
                     <l>Begun to draw with skill the ſhape of ſea and land,</l>
                     <l>To part and multiplie; and ſo from skill to skill</l>
                     <l>We might haue climbed ſoone the ridge of that high hill,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Arts perfection,</hi> in ſigne of their victorie,</l>
                     <l>Crowneth hir Fauorites with euerlaſting glorie.</l>
                     <l>Now, infants we alwaies, ſoone as we learne to ſound</l>
                     <l>The Latine, Hebrue, Greeke, are going to the ground.</l>
                     <l>We learne but prittle-prattle, and for the deepe inſeeing</l>
                     <l>Of natures ſecreſies, and of that onely Being</l>
                     <l>That makes all things to be, we labour, neuer ſtaying,</l>
                     <l>Well to decline a Verbe, or find ſome prety ſaying:</l>
                     <l>Of letters and ſyllabs to way the quantitie,</l>
                     <l>Old knowing naught without maſters auctoritie:</l>
                     <l>Who teach vs how to read, and put into our pawes</l>
                     <l>Some little Chriſcroſrow, in ſtead of ciuill lawes,</l>
                     <l>And for <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and for that holy wrighting</l>
                     <l>Where God himſelfe reueales to Readers there delighting.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <div n="8" type="note">
                     <head>8.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O proud rebellion.</hi> A fine deſcription of euils enſuing this confuſion of ſpéech. Firſt, the acquaintance of all mankinde togither, the knot and loue-bond of nations, is ſo looſened and broke, that ſcarre is there founde any remedie for it, ſome of them not thinking on, or not at all caring for others. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11268:17"/>
that onely one language which decked and embelliſhed the acquaintance and fellowſhip of men, that kept them in peace and temper, ſuch as it was, that made them all well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paide, that mooued each one to his dutie, &amp; was much regarded of all, hath loſt all this by this change, and in a word hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhew nor grace of a language: inſomuch as euen at this day the fall of the Tower of Babel is heard from North to South, from Eaſt to Weſt. That is to ſay, in the diuerſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages of ſo many nations we may obſerue almoſt nothing elſe but a kinde of chattering and confuſed ſounde, neither fit, nor comely, nor expreſſing at all the nature of things: At leaſt one people ſo iudgeth of anothers toong. For I pray you what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure taketh a Frenchman to heare a Moſcouite or a Mexican ſpeake? And euen the toongs that we vnderſtand, and ſpeake (as we thinke) reaſonable well, what are they vnto vs in reſpect of our mother toong, or the principall toongs? Thirdly, whereas the nations dwelling fartheſt aſunder, might eaſily haue come togither, béen acquainted and traffiked one with another: Now a man is no ſooner gone out of his owne doores, but he hath much adoo to vnderſtand thoſe that he méeteth withall; and if he ſet foote in any far country, he néedeth interpretours, or muſt haue ſpent a long time before to learne the toong, or elſe muſt ſpeake by ſignes, or alwaies hold his peace, and liue like a domb creature. Fourthly, to amplifie further this miſerie, the Poet ſheweth that if this diſorder had not happened, a man might haue learned in ſhort time all the Liberall ſciences, and gained the top of that hill where <hi>Encyclopaedia,</hi> (that is, the full com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of all Arts) crowneth all ſuch lawfull aſpiring mindes: and in a word, obtained the parfait knowledge of all things; wheras now we ſpende our whole life in the learning wordes of th'He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue, Gréeke &amp; Latine toongs, &amp; that's nothing elſe but babling: and in ſtead of being wel ſéene in the heauenly Philoſophie, and that of this lower worlde, we muſt take paines in ſyllables &amp; words, circuits of ſpéech, and other like exerciſes, vntill we be gray-headed and white-bearded, and ſo end our liues ſcarſe hauing yet attained any ſufficient knowledge of Law, Phyſicke or Diuinitie, that are the chiefe profeſſions. The learned know
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11268:17"/>
how hard a matter it is to haue a good ſtile, which is called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the meaſure of learning; and that <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who hath ſo excellently well ſet it downe, in that woonderfull worke of his, commonly called the Organ, is vnderſtood but of a few. What may a man ſay then of the moſt part of the diſcourſes and ſpéech of men now adayes liuing? It is nothing but babble, it is Babel it ſelfe. I ſpeake not héere of the ſubſtance of things, but of the faſhion, order, and manner that is vſed to make them be conceiued of thoſe to whom we ſpeake, be they neuer ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the toong themſelues. Then of Barbariſme and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, what ſhall a man thinke?</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">9</hi> What ſhall I tell you more?<note place="margin">The Hebrue toong generally ſpoken before the confuſion of toongs.</note> Men ſpoke in eu'ry place</l>
                     <l>That holy Dialect, the language of Gods grace,</l>
                     <l>A parfit toong, that hath no Letter, no ſmall tyttle,</l>
                     <l>But is embelliſhed with myſteries not lyttle.</l>
                     <l>Now ſince this proud reuolt ſeu'rally people prate,</l>
                     <l>Depraued bibble-babbles, baſtard, effeminate,</l>
                     <l>That eu'ry day do chaunge, and looſing all their light,</l>
                     <l>Scarſe vtter any ſound of that firſt language right.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">10</hi> Long ſince the Phrygians and thoſe by Nilus dwelling,</l>
                     <l>Nilus that nouriſheth, and fats the ground by ſwelling,</l>
                     <l>Deſirous to haue tri'de which was of more antiquitie</l>
                     <l>Of their two languages, truſted againſt all equitie</l>
                     <l>The right of eloquence to tender ſtammering,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe that iudgement lackt made iudges of the thing:</l>
                     <l>To wit, two ſucking Babes whom their two Mothers dombe</l>
                     <l>In Hermitages kept, where go man elſe did come:</l>
                     <l>No humain charming voice was heard ſound neare the place</l>
                     <l>Of their toong-ty'de aboad, for whol three twelmonth ſpace.</l>
                     <l>Then being called foorth and ſet betweene the people</l>
                     <l>Of Xanthus and of Nile, they cry with voices feoble,</l>
                     <l>And often cry they, Bec; bec bec is all the ground</l>
                     <l>That either toong can frame or elſe their mouth will ſound.</l>
                     <l>Whereat the Phrygians that knew bec ſignify'de</l>
                     <l>In their owne language Bread, their countenances dy'de</l>
                     <l>With ioy their hart conceiu'd, bicauſe they were ſo bleſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:11268:18"/>To haue on their behalfe obtain'd natures arreſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">11</hi> O fooles, that litle thought how thoſe bec-bleating flocks,</l>
                     <l>That ſhore the tender flowres from off the neybour rocks,</l>
                     <l>Had ſchool'd them to this terme, &amp; that the words Roomiſh,</l>
                     <l>French, Latin, Hebrue, Greeke, Egyptian or Engliſh,</l>
                     <l>Are not brought-forth with vs; but well may be diſcern'd</l>
                     <l>That each language by haunt and by long vſe is learn'd.</l>
                     <l>Onely remaines a powre, this or that ſound to place,</l>
                     <l>Gift naturall to men; as eeke that other grace,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">To ſpeak diuers languages. Men only ſpeake. An anſwere to the obiection ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinct voice of beaſts.</note> Which variably rich, and richly variable,</l>
                     <l>Vs rendreth moſt vnlike heards brute and miſerable.</l>
                     <l>And if thou liſt oppoſe how that the Bull doth bellow,</l>
                     <l>The ſlothfull Aſſe doth bray, the Lion cruell fellow,</l>
                     <l>Now treble rores, now baſe, and by thoſe tunes we finde,</l>
                     <l>They ſeeme right eloquent to make vs know their minde;</l>
                     <l>Surely thoſe are no words, they are but declarations</l>
                     <l>Of their diſquiet ſtur, by meanes of ſome few paſſions;</l>
                     <l>Confuſed ſignes of griefe, and tokens of their ſadnes,</l>
                     <l>Of ioyfulnes, of loue, of hunger, thirſt, and madnes.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">An anſwere to a ſecond obiection taken from the chirping of birds.</note>The like may well be ſaid of that light winged quier</l>
                     <l>That to the verdaunt boughes of buſhes doth retier,</l>
                     <l>Chirping before the ſunne: for though againſt faire weather</l>
                     <l>Two by two, three by three, they ſeeme to talke together,</l>
                     <l>Though their voice bends it ſelfe a hundred thouſand wayes,</l>
                     <l>Though they can deſcant bold a hundred wanton layes,</l>
                     <l>Though great Apolloes ſelfe within their ſchoole was taught,</l>
                     <l>'Tis but a groundleſſe tune of notes intending naught:</l>
                     <l>A thouſand times a day the ſelfeſame ſong repeated,</l>
                     <l>A dombe diſcourſe amids the trembling trees defeated.</l>
                     <l>But onely man hath powre to preach of modeſtie,</l>
                     <l>Of honour, of wiſedome, of force, of equitie,</l>
                     <l>Of God, of heau'n, of earth, of water and of aire,</l>
                     <l>With words of good import, diuers and choſen faire,</l>
                     <l>Vnfolding all his thoughts not by ſome one language:</l>
                     <l>But like to <hi>Scaliger</hi> the woonder of our age,</l>
                     <l>The lampe of learned men, can wiſely ſpeake, and much,</l>
                     <l>In Latine, Hebrue, Greeke, Engliſh, Italian, Dutch,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:11268:18"/>Spaniſh, Arabian, French, and Slauonian,</l>
                     <l>Chaldean, Syrian, and Aethiopian:</l>
                     <l>Who like Chameleon maketh his transformation</l>
                     <l>(O rich, O pliant wit!) to any auctors facion.</l>
                     <l>Great Iulies worthy ſonne, great Siluies yonger brother</l>
                     <l>In Gaſconie renowmd more than was euer other.</l>
                     <l>Now as for Popinjayes that paſſing all their ages</l>
                     <l>Within the pearced grates of thorow-aired cages,<note place="margin">An anſwere to the third obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion touching Parrets.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Doubt not in eloquence to plead with vs for chiefe;</l>
                     <l>Pronounce all thorowout the Chriſtian beliefe;</l>
                     <l>Repeat the praire deuout that from our Sauiour came,</l>
                     <l>And all the houſhold call togither name by name;</l>
                     <l>They like to th'eccho be, our ſounding voices daughter,</l>
                     <l>That through the vaulted Vales importune bableth after,</l>
                     <l>Not weening what ſhe ſaith: in vaine this aire they breake,</l>
                     <l>And ſpeaking without ſenſe, they ſpeake, and nothing ſpeake:</l>
                     <l>Not hearing their owne voice; bicauſe the right language,</l>
                     <l>Naught is but of the minde the right ſounding image:</l>
                     <l>Chiefly when it is ſhort, when it is ſweete and painted,</l>
                     <l>As that wherewith All were, ere Nimrods time, acquainted.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <div n="9" type="note">
                     <head>9.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>What ſhall I tell you more?</hi> Moſes ſaith, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>11.</hi> Chapter, that then (that is, many yéeres after the flood, and about the ſame time when Chams poſteritie left the Eaſt parts to come and dwell in the plaine of Sennaar) the whole earth was one language and one ſpéech, to wit, Noe and his children: and all the families from them iſſued, though they dwelt not togither, yet ſpake they all the ſame language. All of them parted not from the Eaſt to the foreſaid plaine of Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar: but likely enough is their opinion, that holde that Noe and Sem parted not ſo ſoone ſo farre a ſunder, and eſpecially that they accompanied not theſe builders of Babel, who ſought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme, and ſet vp their reſt in this worlde. A man may aſke now what was that onely language they ſpoke in the worlde before the flood, and after, vntill the building of Babel. The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et anſwereth, it was the language of God himſelfe. Héereupon ariſeth two opinions: The firſt is, of thoſe that to honour their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11268:19"/>
countrey, after the example of ſome ancient Heathens, would make vs beléeue they are ſprung of the earth, or fallen from the Moone, and thinke their ſpéech the moſt excellent of all other. The Egyptians and Phrygians haue long ſithence debated this matter, as ſhall be ſaid more at large in the next Section. A fewe yéeres ago a Phiſition of Brabant named <hi>I. Goropius,</hi> ſet foorth a great booke entituled <hi>Origines Antuerpianae,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he aymeth eſpecially at this marke, to prooue the Cymbrike toong (which in his opinion is the baſe Almaine) to be the firſt ſpéech of the world. Since his death a certaine writer of Liege, hath ſet out many other bookes of his about the ſame matter: and in one of them, that is called <hi>Hermathena,</hi> this Cymbrike toong or lowe Dutch, is preferred farre aboue the Romaine, Gréeke and Hebrue. It aſketh a long diſcourſe to anſwere his reaſons: for this time I will anſwere but in a worde: Namely, that all that which he alledgeth for the preheminence of his owne toong, is a méere cauill, that is called in the Schooles, <hi>Petitio principij:</hi> when a Sophyſter taketh for granted that which is expreſly denied him, and he knowes not how to proue. <hi>Goropius</hi> groundeth al his diſcourſe on this: that the Cymbrike toong hath borrowed nothing of any other, and that the Hebrue is comen of it, and euen borroweth of the Cymbrike. This a man will denie <hi>Goropius</hi> and his diſciples: and whereas they ſhewe ſome Hebrue words or Phraſes that reſemble the words and termes of the baſe Almaine, and ſo conclude that Adam ſpake low Dutch, and that the language of Moſes and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets is hard, ambiguous, poore, and borrowed of the Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brike, which they were not well able to follow: I anſwere, that they are deceiued, and that on the contrarie they ought to ſaie, the Hebrue was afore all other toongs; who were begun in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, and haue ſithence brought foorth infinite others, as the high and low Dutch, and other like, now vſed in the world. I woulde the learned profeſſours of principall toongs, woulde finde ſome time to refute th'allegations of <hi>Goropius:</hi> Eſpecially thoſe that make againſt the Hebrue, which he hath too ſaucily diſgraced in the ſecond booke of his <hi>Hermath, Pag. 25. 26. &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond opinion, which I hold with the Poet, is, that the Hebrue toong,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11268:19"/>
incloſed chiefly in the Canonicall bookes of the old Teſtament (which haue béene woonderfully preſerued vntill our time) is the firſt ſpéech of the world, and the ſame that Moſes meant, when he ſaid, the whole earth had one mouth or language, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the building of Babel. The reaſons thereof are touched in a worde by the Poet, who doth hereafter treat of them more at large, as we haue alſo noted in the margent, &amp; meane to ſpeake ſomewhat thereof in the <hi>12.</hi> Annotation. Now whereas this firſt language hath at this day no letter nor worde, but is full of maimes and myſeries, it may be ſaide of euery toong ſince the confuſion: that it is nothing but corrupt iangling, weake, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, and changing euer from time to time, as many haue already ſhewed heretofore. The Gréeke and Latine toongs haue changed fiue or ſixe times: and the learned know what wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling there hath béene about the writing, pronouncing, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of their termes &amp; phraſes. Then what is to be ſaid of the Gréekiſh and Latiniſh toongs, thoſe that are but apes of the other? What of the barbarous, ſtrange, and new toongs? or of thoſe whoſe fooliſh pronunciation onely no man can abide, or of others that by vſe, time, and force of people, are waxen cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant? but this I leaue to ſuch as liſt to comment héereupon at large.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="note">
                     <head>10.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Long ſince the Phrygians.</hi> The Egyptians, being euer great braggers, vaunted long ago that they were the moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent people of the world: a certaine king of theirs named <hi>Pſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metichus</hi> attempted to ſearch out the truth; and for that end thought méete by ſome meanes to diſcouer what was the firſt language of the world: Thus, he tooke two new-borne babes, and deliuered them vnto ſhepheards to be nourſed, commanding they ſhould be brought vp in a ſecret ſtaule, there to ſucke the milke of goates, and ſtraitly forbidding, that none ſhould come there to pronounce any word before them: then after a certaine time when they were of age, they ſhould be left alone, and made to faſt a while. Now ſo ſoone as they were paſt two yéeres olde, their gouernour hauing in all points accompliſhed the kings commandement, came to open the ſtaule, and then the two chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren began to crie <hi>Bec, bec:</hi> the ſhepheard ſaid not a word: they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11268:20"/>
repeat ſtill the words: and he let his maſter vnderſtand therof, who cauſed the children to be brought ſecretly vnto him, and heard them ſpeake. So when the meaning of the word was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and th'Egyptians vnderſtood it ſignified bread in the Phry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian toong, they graunted the preheminence of antiquitie vnto the Phrygians. <hi>Herodotus</hi> writeth that the prieſts of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> in the citie of <hi>Memphis,</hi> told him the ſame tale. There are ſome others that thinke theſe babes were brought vp of dombe nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: howſoeuer it be, ſure it is that the pride of the Egyptians was by ſome ſuch deuiſe daunted. <hi>Suidas,</hi> touching the very point, ſaith that babes nouriſhed of a goate, muſt néedes crie ſomthing like a goate, and ſuch was the ſound of the word <hi>Bec;</hi> a méete reward for his wiſedome that made ſuch a triall. The Grecians in old time were woont to call an old dotard <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, a word compoſed of <hi>Bec</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the moone: the ſame is turned into a prouerbe which <hi>Eraſmus</hi> expoundeth. But <hi>Goropius</hi> in the <hi>5.</hi> and <hi>9.</hi> booke of his <hi>Origines</hi> plaieth the ſubtill Sophiſter, as his maner is, and vſeth his beake vpon the word <hi>Bec:</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, ſince bec in low Dutch ſignifies bread, and <hi>Pſammeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> his babes called for bec, that ſo long ago they ſpoke lowe Dutch; whereupon it followeth, that his toong is the moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of the world. He calleth alſo his diſcourſes vpon the ſame <hi>Becceſelanea,</hi> offering the ſubiect of a comedie to ſome new <hi>Ariſtophanes.</hi> But let vs conſider the anſwers of the Poet to the Phrygians and to <hi>Goropius.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="note">
                     <head>11.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O fooles, that little thought.</hi> The firſt anſwere is, that this word <hi>Bec</hi> that the children ſpoke, was a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed ſound com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming néere the crie of goates: And how could they aſke bread, ſéeing that they vnderſtood it not, neuer heard it ſpoken by any bodie, neuer heard the meaning of it? The ſecond is, that words are not borne with vs, but that we learne them by haunt &amp; long vſage. If they were borne with vs, doubtles theſe infants would haue ſpoken as well other words: for the vnderſtanding being mooued, the belly pinched with hunger, would not content it ſelfe to expreſſe his paſſion in one ſyllable. The third is, that men are onely the right and proper ſpeakers, yet if they be not taught it, and thereto faſhioned, but are brought vp among
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11268:20"/>
beaſts, in ſtead of a right &amp; framed ſpéech, they ſhall make but a ſound and crie confuſed like vnto beaſts. In a word, I take this diſcourſe of <hi>Herodotus,</hi> touching the two infants and their <hi>Bec,</hi> to be but a tale made vpon pleaſure, and a very heard-ſay; and there againſt I oppoſe the antiquitie of the Hebrue toong. Yet if I were bound to beléeue <hi>Herodotus,</hi> I would ſay the Phrygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>Bec</hi> was drawen from the Hebrues <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Lechem.</hi> The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Goropius</hi> will confeſſe that the Phrygians are come from the ſucceſſours of Noe: ſo can it not ſéeme ſtrange vnto them, that I ſay the Phrygians retaining ſome tokens of their grandfathers language, haue (like infinite others) lengthened and ſhortened the moſt part of the words: ſome whereof yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine whole, to witnes the antiquitie and principalitie of the Hebrue toong. After this the Poet anſwereth thoſe that build vpon the vnframed noiſe of beaſts, the chirping and chattering of birdes, and the babling of Parrets, to prooue the birth of ſpéech with vs, and caſt a cloud ouer that perfection he graunted onely to the firſt language; and ſo he ſaith that man onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with reaſon, is the onely creature on earth capable of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, ordered, important, and proper ſpéech, and further ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth many ſeuerall toongs: whereof he bringeth in for example the learned <hi>Scaliger.</hi> Hence it enſueth that a man cannot learne to ſpeake, if he be brought vp among beaſts that haue no reaſon whereby to deſerue the name of a ſpéech, or to vſe the ſame aright: or if he be brought vp with ſuch as are dombe, of whom he can learne nothing but ſignes &amp; confuſed ſounds, he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake treatably, nor vnderſtande any thing, except another do ſpeake firſt vnto him, and make him vnderſtande the ſpéech with often repeating: As appéereth not onely in yoong children, but in the oldeſt men alſo, who learne as long as they liue the words and names of thoſe very things which they haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſéene before. It followeth then, that all the diſcourſe of the Phrygians <hi>Bec</hi> is a deuiſed tale, &amp; therefore vnwoorthy for them to buyld vpon, that go about to prooue the Phrygian toong, or theirs that would draw their pedegrée from the Phrygians, to be the firſt language of the world. Another man may finde in his owne toong a many like words, and drawe thence as good
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11268:21"/>
concluſions as <hi>Goropius</hi> doth. But a ſtrange thing it is, that the heathen authors haue ſaid nothing, nor made any mention in their bookes of the beginnings and occaſions of diuerſitie of toongs: eſpecially that the Grecians, and other ſuch learned peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that haue profeſſed the knowledge of all things, knew not the beginning of their owne language. Moſes onely hath ſet vs downe this notable hiſtorie, &amp; opened vnto the Heathen the ſpring of their toongs. And this further is to be woondered at in the hiſtorie of Babel, that the Hebrue toong alone, as being the firſt of the world, hath remained among that people that were the Church of God, where the Meſſias was borne, and from whence aroſe the preaching of the Goſpell, touching the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the promiſed Sauiour: which Goſpell hath ſithence by the gift of toongs and miniſterie of the Apoſtles ouerſpread al the parts of the world. Thus Moſes handling the beginning of toongs, prooueth his hiſtorie to haue long fore-gone all others, and therewithall engraueth vpon the gates and wals of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Tower of Babel, a godly warning to all men, to flie and auoide Atheiſme, and all vain-glorious follie, which buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Towers againſt heauen, and rebelleth againſt God: who ſuffereth the wicked to aduaunce and hoyſe vp themſelues the ſpace of ſome fewe monthes or yéeres, to the end he may giue them a fearfull ouerthrow at length. What woulde the preſumption of man haue done (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) when algate the top of this Tower had raught vnto the cloudes? It is humilitie that lifteth vp the hart on high, to the Lorde, not againſt the Lord: ſhée it is that leadeth vs the true, right, and ſure way to heauen. Theſe fewe words I thought good to adde vnto the reſt, bicauſe the proud aſpiring mind of man can not be ſufficiently diſcouered, nor to much cried out on. Wheras theſe builders buſily forecaſt in their minde, and laboured to make themſelues renowmed among their poſteritie, &amp; thought men of ſome woorth, let vs remember that the true praiſe conſiſteth not in works of goodly outward ſhew, but in ſuch as are good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede, and approoued of God. So let vs returne to the text of the Poet, who hauing touched in a worde the beginning of toongs, and refuted ſome contrarie obiections, ſheweth now
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11268:21"/>
which of all the toongs that haue béene, are, or ſhall be in the world, ought to be accounted the chiefe and moſt auncient, and whereof a man may truly ſay, it is the moſt excellent of all other.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now when I duly way how <hi rend="sup">12</hi> th' Ebrue toong doth ſhew<note place="margin">The Hebrue toong moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And readily expreſſe in words a very few</l>
                     <l>Moſt comberſome conceits, and through each ſecret plight</l>
                     <l>Of reaſons laberynth affoords the Reader light,</l>
                     <l>Much better than the Greeke with hir Synonymons,<note place="margin">The firſt reaſon.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hit lofty Metaphors, hir bould Epithetons,</l>
                     <l>Hir compounding of words, hir tenſes and hir caſes,</l>
                     <l>And of ſo great requeſt a thouſand other graces:</l>
                     <l>When I conſider well how that the ſchoole Rabine<note place="margin">The ſecond reaſon.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Findes in the letter-row of that language diuine</l>
                     <l>All we beleeue with hart, all that with eie we ſee,</l>
                     <l>And that within the law all Arts compriſed be:</l>
                     <l>Be it that with much ado one curiouſly aſſaies</l>
                     <l>The letters of each word to turne a hundred waies;</l>
                     <l>(For in Arithmetike as cyphers changing roome</l>
                     <l>Doth either much enhaunſe or much abate the ſomme,</l>
                     <l>So th' Anagramme ſtraight knits or elſe vndoth the grace</l>
                     <l>Of words whoſe letters take right enterchange of place)</l>
                     <l>Or beit to put togither thou rightly do deuiſe</l>
                     <l>The numbers myſticall that from the letters riſe</l>
                     <l>Of ſome one Hebrue word, and vnder that one name</l>
                     <l>Another findeſt hid in number like the ſame;</l>
                     <l>Or that ſome word is know'n by ſome one element,</l>
                     <l>Or by ſome onely word a parfit ſpeech is ment,</l>
                     <l>As in an Embleme ſhort th' Egyptian ſilence</l>
                     <l>Was myſtically woont to preſſe a long ſentnce.</l>
                     <l>When I conſider well that from th' Eaſt-Indian ſand</l>
                     <l>Vnto the flaming mount that borders Ireland,<note place="margin">the third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>From cold Tartarian ſeas to ſchorched Tambuts ſhore,</l>
                     <l>Thou Sunne no people ſee'ſt ſo voide of gentle lore,</l>
                     <l>No men ſo ignorant of Gods moſt holy law,</l>
                     <l>But they retaine as yet ſome words of Hebrue Saw;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:11268:22"/>And but their letters do (though out of order ſet)</l>
                     <l>Come neere the holy names of Moſes Alphabet;</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The fourth reaſon.</note>When with my ſelfe I way the ſacred counterpawn</l>
                     <l>Of Gods old Teſtament was in thoſe letters draw'n;</l>
                     <l>That VRIM, that the DREAME, and that the VISION wiſe</l>
                     <l>But in the Hebrue toong ſpake not their Propheſies;</l>
                     <l>And that th' Eternals ſelfe would with his finger deigne</l>
                     <l>To graue in Hebrue words his Law on Marbles twaine;</l>
                     <l>And that ſince many yeeres the meſſengers Diuine</l>
                     <l>Did preach the ioyfull Word in language Paleſtine;</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The fift reaſon.</note>And when I farther way, that th' ancient Patriarchs</l>
                     <l>Had not their names impos'd without ſome reaſons marks,</l>
                     <l>Yea ſuch as fully ſhew'd (and that with great moment)</l>
                     <l>Of their whole courſe of life ſome famous accident,</l>
                     <l>And that a man may ſee that eu'ry ancient name</l>
                     <l>Both by ſound and by ſence from Hebrue language came,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>As <hi>Eue,</hi> is conſterd life; <hi>Cain,</hi> firſt of all begot;</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                        <hi>Adam,</hi> create of clay; <hi>Abel,</hi> that profits not;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Seth,</hi> ſet in others place; and he ſurnamed Reſt,</l>
                     <l>That ſaw th'all-ſtroying flood below the ground ſuppreſt;</l>
                     <l>I cannot chooſe but grant, though Greece do fret and fome,</l>
                     <l>The ſacred elder right to th' Ebrewes Idiome.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Hebrue toong.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">13</hi> Then do I thee ſalute, O euer-running Spring</l>
                     <l>Of reaſons portraiture, Phraſe of th' eternall king,</l>
                     <l>Thou brightly-ſhining Pearle, Queene-mother of languages,</l>
                     <l>That ſpotles haſt eſcap'd the Dungeon of all ages,</l>
                     <l>That haſt no word but wai'th, whoſe very elements</l>
                     <l>Are full of hidden ſence, whoſe points haue Sacraments,</l>
                     <l>O holy Dialect, in thee the proper names</l>
                     <l>Of men, towns, countries, are th' abridgments of their fames</l>
                     <l>And memorable deedes: the names of winged bands,</l>
                     <l>Of water-habitants, of armies of the lands,</l>
                     <l>Are open treatiſes, whereout each one might gather</l>
                     <l>Their natures hiſtories, before th' heau'n-rowling father</l>
                     <l>By raging anger mou'd with flaming Symeteer</l>
                     <l>The way to Eden karu'd from theſe baſe cuntries heere.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Adam gaue He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue names to all</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">14</hi> For when Adam, in ſigne of his preheminence,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:11268:22"/>Names did in true Elyſe to all creatures diſpence<note place="margin">creatures accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then when before his eies in muſter generall</l>
                     <l>Two by two, ſide by ſide, in ranke they marched all,</l>
                     <l>He choſe them all ſo fit, that eu'ry learned eare</l>
                     <l>Bearing the ſound to minde, the maruailes might eke beare</l>
                     <l>Wherewith th'al-fourming word did richly beautifie</l>
                     <l>Both thoſe that liue in wet, and thoſe that liue in drie.<note place="margin">He enriched the toong with Verbes and clauſes.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">15</hi> And for each Body muſt ſuffer ſome thing, or do,</l>
                     <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he the Nounes had fram'd, the Verbes he ioyn'd therto;</l>
                     <l>Then, more to beautifie this goodly ground of pleading,</l>
                     <l>Many a tittle made, that ſerues to grace the reading,</l>
                     <l>The parts of moſt account to ſow togither fit;</l>
                     <l>As doth a little glue two mightie planchers knit:</l>
                     <l>And farther ſerues as doth the wauing plume of feathers</l>
                     <l>That on the chamfred top of gliſtring helmet weathers:</l>
                     <l>To marble Images, as footſtals do and baſes</l>
                     <l>To ſiluer cups their eares, to veluet robes their laces.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">16</hi> This toong that Adam ſpoke,<note place="margin">The Hebrue toong continued generally ſpoken, from Adam to Nimrod, then it remained onely in the familie of Heber: whence it was called Hebrue.</note> till in bad time arriu'd</l>
                     <l>That heau'n-aſſaulting prince, ſincerely was deriu'd</l>
                     <l>From father vnto ſonne, the worlds circumference</l>
                     <l>Did throughly ſound the tunes of hir rich eloquence:</l>
                     <l>But then as partiall full quickly was ſhe gone</l>
                     <l>To Hebers familie, or bicauſe he was none</l>
                     <l>Of that rebellious band, or wiſely did abide</l>
                     <l>Far from the Sennar plaine in that vnhappie tide;</l>
                     <l>Or if he thither were among the reſt conſtrain'd</l>
                     <l>In corners worſhipt God and ſecretly complain'd,</l>
                     <l>And ſo with ſlauiſh armes holpe them to build thoſe wals</l>
                     <l>Which in deſpight he vow'd vnto the deepe entrals</l>
                     <l>Of darkſom Tartarus: as gally-ſlaue in giues,</l>
                     <l>That combating the ſea moſt miſerably ſtriues</l>
                     <l>Againſt his libertie, and curſeth in his hart</l>
                     <l>Thoſe for whom night and day he practiſeth his art:</l>
                     <l>Or beit th' eternall God with his hands euer-giuing</l>
                     <l>Preuenting as it were the works of men well liuing,</l>
                     <l>For his owne honors ſake, and of his onely grace,</l>
                     <l>This treaſure left in truſt with <hi>Hebers</hi> holy race;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:11268:23"/>When as of Maſons proud the reſt full ill beſted</l>
                     <l>A hundred thouſand waies the ſame disfigured,</l>
                     <l>And eu'ry one diſperſ'd where deſtinie them taried</l>
                     <l>Into a new-found land a new-made language caried.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <div n="12" type="note">
                     <head>12.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Th'Ebrue toong.</hi> He propoundeth fiue reaſons, whereby he is induced to beléeue that the Hebrue is the firſt toong of all, whatſoeuer the Gréeke and others do alledge for themſelues.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is, that this toong compriſeth much matter in few words, is very ſignificant, briefely and plainly expreſſeth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a man can thinke, and when it is requiſite to diſcouer the moſt ſecret and hidden plights of the hart, ſhe ſlippeth none, but for all things hath words liuely, pleaſant, waightie and of great import: and for hir circuits of ſpéech and long diſcourſes, they are more woonderful then the beſt and ſwéeteſt the Gréeke hath: which not withſtanding hir ſtore of ſelfe-meaning words, hir bould and far-fetcht Epithites, hir cunning Metaphores, hir words compounded, hir tenſes and other fine deuiſes, is no more comparable to the other, than the chirping of a Goldfinch is to the ſong of the Nightingall. Proofe hereof may be made by the earneſt and diligent conſideration, and waying the wordes, ſentences, &amp; diſcourſes of the Hebrue with thoſe of the Gréeke, and all others: not onely in Grammars and Dictionaries, but euen in whole bookes and volumes. It ſhall ſuffiſe me to wage and lay the booke of Pſalmes onely, or the workes of Salomon, or Iob, or of Eſay, againſt all other auctours: and I dare bould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly auouch, that in one of theſe a man ſhall finde almoſt in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chapter, more elegance, ſtate and maieſtie, more figures, and more of all kinde of ornaments for a diſcourſe, than in all the tedious works of thoſe that mans wiſedom ſetteth-by ſo much. I ſpeake not now of the matter and ſubſtance of things, which neuertheleſſe is in this toong as happily expreſſed as in any other; let them ſtraine themſelues neuer ſo much, they are not able but very groſſely and a-farre-off to make a ſhew of that which this other painteth out in orient colours, what matter ſoeuer it hath occaſion to vtter.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond reaſon is, that the Rabbines or Hebrue Doctors
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11268:23"/>
(men woondrous carefull to preſerue the whole bodie of the old Teſtament, ſo as the leaſt letter, point, and accent, they haue counted ouer and againe often times) haue noted in the <hi>22.</hi> letters of the Hebrue Alphabet, either apart or togither conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, all the ſecrets of Diuinitie and of Philoſophie, both na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and morall. This is a notable thing in the Hebrue toong, that all the letters haue their proper ſignification: and that the letters of moſt of the principall toongs in the world haue taken their beginning from them: as alſo that the primitiue words, and thoſe of whom infinite others are deriued in diuers princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall toongs, are drawne from the letters, ſyllables and words of the Hebrue. To ſay nothing of the excellencie of hir accents, and the propertie of hir vowels: the Rabbines haue further found out many ſecrets by diuers way-turning and alter-placing the letters of Hebrue words: and that which the Gréekes &amp; others haue after their example inuented, is nothing in compariſon. For there is ſcarce any word in the Hebrue, but being inuerted (as may eaſily be done, and ſomtimes two, thrée, or fower waies, as the number of the letters are) offereth to our conſideration another word, either of like ſenſe, or contrarie: or making rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the firſt, giueth thereto ſuch light, beautie and liuelihood, that it is woonderfull to behold. Againe, oftentimes a Nowne or other word, yea a letter, importeth a whole ſentence, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Egyptians Hieroglyphikes, inuented of them to the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Hebrue letters and words, yet nothing in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of them. This matter would require a whole volume, to be written according to Art, by the hand of ſome one that were wel ſeene in the toongs: and I could name thrée paire yet liuing that are well able to do it. In the meane ſeaſon, whoſoeuer is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſearch further herein, let him read the <hi>Harmonie of the World,</hi> written by <hi>Franciſcus Georgius,</hi> and <hi>Guido Faber:</hi> the <hi>Heptap.</hi> of <hi>Ioannes Picus,</hi> Earle of Mirandula, the <hi>Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phickes</hi> of <hi>I. Goropius,</hi> from the beginning of the ſeuenth booke, to the end of the ſixtéenth: thrée bookes of <hi>I. Reuclinus <hi>De arte Cabaiistica,</hi>
                        </hi> and other thrée bookes of his <hi>De Verbo mirabili,</hi> the <hi>Cabala</hi> of <hi>Picus,</hi> with the interpretations of <hi>Angelus Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goneuenſis</hi> thereupon. Further, much good matter to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:11268:24"/>
a man may finde in <hi>Theſauro linguae ſanctae,</hi> ſet out by <hi>S. Pag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus,</hi> and after augmented by many other learned profeſſors of this toong. Sée further the <hi>Syriac Institut, &amp;c.</hi> of <hi>Caninius:</hi> the <hi>Mithridates</hi> of <hi>C. Geſnerus:</hi> the <hi>Alphabet</hi> in <hi>12.</hi> toongs of <hi>Poſtella,</hi> and his booke, <hi>De antiquitate linguae Hebraica,</hi> there are many ſuch Treatiſes ſet foorth by diuers learned men: whereout, and of the bookes aforenamed, may be gathered infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite proofes of that which the Poet hath touched in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reaſon.</p>
                     <p>The thirde is, that there liues no nation vnder the cope of heauen, but kéepeth ſtill ſome words of Hebrue in their ſpéech; Firſt, the Caldean, Syrian, Arabian, Egyptian, Perſian, Ethiopian, and many other, as the Gotthicke, Troglodytick, Punick, are ſo deriued thence, that they come as néere it as Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian to Latine, ſome more, ſome leſſe. Secondly, the Gréeke, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and thoſe others, that are farther off, haue yet here and there ſome words that we muſt néedes grant, are ſprong from the ſame fountaine: a man may ſet downe a many of them, but it were too long here to coate the examples. Thirdly, the rootes of many words that are taken to be Gréeke or ſome other toong, are founde to be Hebrue, as <hi>Franciſcus Iunius</hi> hath plainly ſhewed in his learned oration <hi>De linguae Hebraeae antiquitate &amp; praestantia.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The fourth reaſon is, that the doctrine of the old Teſtament, which is the doctrine of the firſt and moſt ancient people of the world, was not written but in Hebrue. No man denieth that the people that came of Sem the ſonne of Noe, is the moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: among theſe remained the Church of God and the Hebrue toong. God ſpake not but in the Hebrue toong by the high prieſt that wore the ſacred Ephod, and the breaſt-plate of iudgement, whereon was ſet <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Vrim &amp; Thummim</hi> (words ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lights &amp; perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) which ſome thinke was the <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> or four-letered name <hi>Iehoua,</hi> contained within the breſt-plate: others ſay it was the ranks of thoſe twelue precious ſtones there enchaſed, that on them had ingrauen the names of the twelue tribes of Iſrael: as if it were a repetition of that which Moſes ſaith in the <hi>17.18.19.</hi> and <hi>20.</hi> verſes of the <hi>28.</hi> chapter of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11268:24"/>
                        <hi>Exodus,</hi> where he ſpeaketh of <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Vrim &amp; Thummim</hi> in the <hi>30.</hi> verſe: others hold they were certaine names: others are of diuers other opinions. Some late writers thinke thoſe words were ingrauen in the breaſt-plate: This is a ſecret, the ſearch whereof (whether one diſpute of the words, or what they meant, or whats become of them, &amp;c.) is very painfull and néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe; for that now ſithence the comming of Chriſt we ought to follow the truth it ſelfe, and not ſtay vpon ſhadowes. Theſe words doubtles gaue to vnderſtand, that all light and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction commeth of our Sauiour, in whom all the fulnes of the Godhead bodily dwelleth, in whom are hid all the treaſures of vnderſtanding and knowledge, who is the light of his Church, that is made vnto vs of God his father wiſedome, iuſtice, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and holines. In all iudgements, demaunds, oracles, and reuelations that were made by <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> (as may be gathered out of the <hi>27.</hi> chapter of <hi>Numbers,</hi> the firſt booke of <hi>Samuel</hi> the <hi>13.</hi> and <hi>30.</hi> chapters, and other places where aduiſe and counſell was aſked of God, and anſwere was made by the mouth of the high prieſt) there appéered a cléere light, a ſure truth and perfection: all which in Chriſt is accompliſhed. Now theſe demaunds &amp; anſwers were propounded &amp; rendred in the Hebrue toong, long time before any other language was vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. For ſo ſoone after their ſcattering at Babel they could not well be incorporated into a common-wealth: and as for religion, that was not kept but in the race of Sem, as Moſes plainly declareth all through the hiſtorie of Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Concerning the Prophets, their dreames &amp; viſions, God ſpake not, they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not, neither anſwered or taught they the Church but in the Hebrue; that ſignificant, vnmingled, holy, chaſte &amp; heauenly toong; wheras others liſpe and ſtammer out vncertaine ſounds, and are infinite waies defiled through the diſhoneſt, fooliſh, erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and vngodly diſcourſes of their inuentours: I except the bookes of the new Teſtament, and all writings drawen from the cléere fountaines of holy Scripture, beſides the which there is nothing but vanitie, filth, wickednes, and vngodlines in the world. Moreouer, the Lord himſelfe ſetting downe his law to his people, and writing it twiſe with his owne finger, and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:11268:25"/>
with his owne mouth to Moſes and his other ſeruants in the Mount, vſed the Hebrue toong. So did the Angels and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and Ieſus Chriſt ſpake the Syriacke, a toong ſo deriued of the Hebrue, that they are very like; as their Grammars de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare. The Apoſtles ſpake diuers toongs, and wrote alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the people and perſons with whom they had to doe: yet for all that in their bookes may be noted an infinite many of phraſes borrowed of the Hebrue: as the learned interpreters of the new Teſtament haue exactly ſhewed.</p>
                     <p>The fift and laſt reaſon ſet downe by the Poet is, that the Hebrue words, eſpecially the proper names (ſome are alledged for example, and many other may be added) are of great waight and importance: for ſomtimes they lay open vnto vs the chiefe things that doe befall the perſon ſo named. Nay further, if a man would take the paines to change the order of letters, he may finde in them many goodly myſteries. The Gréekes haue found the way, and followed it in the interpretation of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per names: but they come far ſhort of the liuelyhood and maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of the Hebrues, who begun the thing before them many hundred yéeres. As for other toongs the moſt part of their proper names haue no meaning; they are deuiſed at-all auentures; ſo are they right tokens of barbariſme. Som toongs there are more happie and plentious than others in this behalfe: but their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations are for the moſt part vncertaine, eſpecially if the Roote thereof come not from or néere the Hebrue. Héerehence againe the curious reader may take occaſion of a large commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie: I leaue it vnto him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="note">
                     <head>13.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then doe I thee ſalute.</hi> It is not without cauſe, that the Poet ſtraight vpon the former diſcourſe, vſeth theſe words: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the excellencie of the Hebrue toong, and that he ſetteth out in ſo few verſes hir wonderful perfections, each one of them requiring a large treatiſe, and himſelfe being vnable to ſhut vp ſo great matters in ſo few words. For example ſake let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but very briefly thoſe thrée points that the Poet héere tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: to wit, that the 22. Hebrue letters are full of hidden ſenſe; that the proper names of perſons, countries, and cities in this toong are as much as abridgements of their life and déedes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:11268:25"/>
that the names of birds, beaſts and fiſhes, containe the hiſtorie of their natures, howbeit ſince the fall of Adam the knowledge thereof is greatly darkened. To make the Reader ſomewhat more deſirous to enter meditation hereon, I will ſet him downe ſome examples. Concerning the myſteries of th'Hebrue Letter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>Euſebius</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Ierom</hi> in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Paul. vrbic.</hi> which is the <hi>155.</hi> expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth them, as I ſhal ſhew you in our own toong. The firſt letter <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Aleph</hi> ſignifieth doctrine, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Beth</hi> a houſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Ghimel</hi> Fulnes, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Daleth</hi> Tables, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>He</hi> This, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Vau</hi> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Zain</hi> That or ſhe there, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Cheth</hi> Life, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Teth</hi> Good, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Ioth</hi> Beginning, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Chaph</hi> a Hand, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Lamed</hi> Diſcipline, or the Hart, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Mem</hi> Theirs, or of theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Nun</hi> Continuall, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Samech</hi> Aide or ſuccour, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Ain</hi> a Spring, or an Eie, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Phe</hi> a Mouth, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Sade</hi> Iuſtice, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Coph</hi> Calling, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Reſch</hi> a Head, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Schin</hi> Téeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Tau</hi> Signes. All which may be thus put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither and expounded. The <hi>doctrine</hi> of the Church, which is the <hi>houſe</hi> of God, is found in the <hi>fulnes</hi> of the <hi>Tables:</hi> that is, the holy Scriptures. <hi>This</hi> doctrine and that <hi>fulnes</hi> of the tables is the <hi>life;</hi> for what life can we haue without the knowledge of holy Scripture? Out <hi>of theſe</hi> we learne Ieſus Chriſt, who is the life of them that beléeue. And although this knowledge be excellent and parfit in God, yet as for vs, we know not but in part, we ſée as it were by a glaſſe in darknes: But when we ſhal aſcend vp into heauen, &amp; become like vnto the Angels, then the doctrine of the houſe, and the fulnes of the tables of Gods truth, ſhall be accompliſhed: then ſhall we ſée face to face the <hi>Good</hi> prince (to wit, God himſelf the Soueraign Good, who is the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> of all things) euen as he is in his owne nature. In the mean-time we muſt lay <hi>Hand</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke of our <hi>Calling,</hi> by the meanes of a right <hi>Diſcipline</hi> or a true <hi>Hart,</hi> aſſuring our ſelues that we ſhall finde <hi>Continuall Succour</hi> in this heauenly truth, which is the <hi>Spring</hi> or <hi>Eie</hi> of the <hi>Mouth</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> namely Chriſt our <hi>Head,</hi> whoſe <hi>Calling</hi> is in <hi>Signes,</hi> or marks of <hi>Teeth</hi> or framed voice of the Scripture. I deſire th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ader to take in good part this ſhort Allegorie that I am bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>d make vpon the Hebrue letters; and if he deſire more in this kinde; let him repaire to the Rootes of th' eſſential words of theſe letters, there
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11268:26"/>
may he view the matter more at large. For this time it ſhall ſuffice to haue ſhot this arrow at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marke our Poet aymed at.</p>
                     <p>Now for the ſecond point touching the names of ſeuerall men, of nations and cities, I will note you a couple of examples of each: <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Abraham</hi> ſignifieth A father of many, ſo was his houſhold much increaſed temporally and ſpiritually, he is the father of all the Beléeuers, whoſe number is vncountable. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Moſes</hi> ſignifieth Taken out of the waters, ſo was he by <hi>Pharoes</hi> daughter, when his mother, loth to haue him ſlaine ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the kings cruell commandement, had laid him foorth in a pitched flaſket by the riuers brinke, <hi>Exod. 2.</hi> By him alſo God guided his people through the waters of the red ſea, and wrought many miracles. The Arabians are a people who euen at this day haue no certaine place of abode, they wander ſtill vp and downe the champion countreyes and wildernes, they are famous théeues, and lurking in ſecret places make often ſallies out vpon their neighbours, and ſet vpon all paſſengers vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares. Their name commeth of the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Arab,</hi> by <hi>Ain</hi> in the firſt coniugation <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Hearib,</hi> which ſignifieth to mingle day and night togither: and bicauſe that in a deſert and waſte place all things are confuſed, as if day and night were mingled togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, therefore the countrey for the ſituation is called <hi>Arabia.</hi> This Verbe agréeth right with another <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Arab,</hi> written by <hi>Aleph,</hi> which ſignifieth to lie in ambuſh, or to lurke in dennes as théeues and rauening beaſts doe. The Egyptians in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Mitſraim</hi> bicauſe of their ſtrong holds and places of defence, that haue béen long amongſt them: the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue word is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Tſor</hi> that ſignifieth to Truſſe cloſe togither: In ſome places of Scripture Egypt is called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Rahab,</hi> that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Proud: ſo ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d they haue alwaies béen high-minded and greater braggers than any other people. Now for cities <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſignifieth The viſion of peace, and iuſt according to the truth: for the peace and grace of God hath béene ſéene and continued vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> place many hundred yéeres, and chiefly bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> figure of the Church militant and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant; as often mention is made of the new and heauenly Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. <hi>Babilon</hi> commeth of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Babel,</hi> which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:11268:26"/>
of the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Balal</hi> to confound, mingle, or trouble, as water when it is mudded. For ſo indéed the earthy <hi>Babel,</hi> that was in <hi>Chaldaea,</hi> hath made a hotchpotch of the world: and that <hi>Babel,</hi> the ſpirituall, that is ſpoken of in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> hath made ſo many confuſions, that it is vnpoſſible to name them all.</p>
                     <p>There remaineth the third point, touching Birds, foure-foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beaſts, and fiſhes, whereof and euery of them I will name two onely, for a patterne, leaſt I ſéeme too long in the anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. The Storke, ſo commended for hir loue towarde thoſe by whom ſhe receiued life, is called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Chaſida,</hi> that is to ſay, dutifull, louing, and religious. The Eagle is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Neſcher</hi> that commeth néere to <hi>Shor</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Iaſhar,</hi> the one ſignifieth to looke, the other to be rightfull: and this bird of all other hath the ſharpeſt ſight, and looketh againſt the ſunne. There is further a liuely deſcription of this bird in the <hi>39.</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Iob,</hi> as alſo of the Auſtrich, and many other in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture. The horſe, called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Sus,</hi> is thought to come of the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Naſas,</hi> if rather this Verbe be not thence deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, which ſignifieth to aduaunce himſelfe: for it is the braueſt and fierceſt of all other foure-footed beaſts: as <hi>Iob</hi> finely deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth him in the <hi>39.</hi> chapter. The Hebrues haue thrée names for a Lion; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Arieh,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Labi</hi> and <hi>Laijſch:</hi> the firſt commeth of a Verbe that ſignifieth to ſnatch, and teare in ſunder: the ſecond of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Leb,</hi> that ſignifieth the Hart, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Laab,</hi> to be in ſolitarie and deſert places: the third is commonly interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a great and roring Lion, not vnlike the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Loſh,</hi> that ſignifieth to ſurpriſe or deuoure, for tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his beaſt rampeth-vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſwalloweth vp his pray. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>hales and great fiſhes are called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Thannim,</hi> Snakes, Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>nts, or Dragons, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are of a great length, and turne and fould themſelues euery way, and are no leſſe dangerous in the ſea than ſerpents and dragons on the land. In the <hi>40.</hi> chapter of <hi>Iob</hi> that great fiſh is called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> which ſome de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> of the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Lauah,</hi> which ſignifieth to borrow or take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or his recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: bicauſe the Whale ſéemeth to play vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> downe the ſea, as in a place borrowed for recreation. The C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>codile, that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth both on land and water, is called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Hatſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> and ſéemeth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:11268:27"/>
to come of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Tſab,</hi> which ſignifieth the couering of a Chariot, bicauſe this mightie creature hath ſo long and ſo thicke a ſkin. Moreouer, th'Hebrues of the whole kinde of fiſhes ſpeake commonly as if they were of another world, bicauſe they are ſo farre parted and ſeuered from the ſight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of men: they make thrée ſorts of them, which they expreſſe by the words <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Dagh,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Thannim,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Leuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</hi> This haue I added the more to ſhew the liuelihood and naturall importance of this toong, and héerewith I will content my ſelfe at this time, deſiring that ſome other, ſtirred vp by my example, would take this matter in hand, and diſcourſe of it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more at large.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="note">
                     <head>14</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>For when Adam.</hi> Moſes ſaith plainly, in the <hi>19.</hi> and <hi>20.</hi> verſes of the ſecond Chapter of <hi>Geneſis:</hi> That God made all the beaſts of the fielde, and foules of the heauen come before <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> to ſée how he would name them, and that howſoeuer he named euery thing liuing, ſo was the name thereof. The Man therefore gaue names vnto all Cattaile, and to the Foules of heauen, and to euery Beaſt of the field. The wiſedome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our firſt father was endued before his fall, importeth thus much, that he ſhould giue méete and couenable names vnto all creatures vnder his dominion: &amp; although the knowledge and ſearch of birds and beaſts names be hard, bicauſe of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mans iudgement now ſince his fall, yet is it not vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as men wel ſéene in the Hebrue toong haue alreadie ſhewed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="note">
                     <head>15</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>15 And for each Bodie. Adam</hi> a man parfitly wiſe before he ſinned, gaue not onely méete names to all creatures, that were (in a maner) the moouables and inſtruments of his houſe, and of this great ſhop of the world, whereof the Lord had made him maſter; but further enriched his language with all maner of ornaments that might be required to make it parfit: So that before his fall he ſpake more eloquently than any mortall man ſince. After he had ſinned, entred ignorance into his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and frowardnes into his affections: which haue made the ſpéech of him and his poſteritie vnfitting, vnparfit, deceiuable, and often falſe, euen in humane and indifferent things, yea ſuch ſometime as we moſt curiouſlie ſtudie vpon:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:11268:27"/>
But the grace of God, the long life of this Patriarch, and his freſh remembrance of the woondrous things that he had ſéene in the Garden of Eden, haue brought to paſſe doubtleſſe, that the conuerſation, inſtruction, reports and authoritie of ſo great a perſonage, had a maruellous force to perſwade and teach all thoſe that were in his ſchoole. For from him had we firſt our Arts &amp; Sciences deriued, &amp; eſpecially the knowledge of the true God. And although ſince his time the things haue béene more and more illightened and parfited, yet muſt we néedes confeſſe that <hi>Adam</hi> was the firſt teacher of them. Who ſo deſireth to know the depth of his wiſedome, let him at his leyſure medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate vpon the foure firſt Chapters of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe there is contained the ſumme of all that all men haue knowne, or ſhall vnto the worlds end. Now out of all doubt it is, that <hi>Adam</hi> taught his children and their poſteritie all theſe things exactly. But Moſes, by the direction of the ſpirit of God, thought it ſufficient to repreſent onely the grounde of things: otherwiſe the world neither had nor would euer be able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the bookes that might be made vpon theſe foure firſt Chapters.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="note">
                     <head>16</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This toong that Adam ſpoke.</hi> The firſt world conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued <hi>1656.</hi> yéeres. <hi>Adam</hi> liued <hi>930.</hi> yéeres, his poſteritie kept his language, and although they poſſeſſed with their tents and dwellings a large péece of ground, yet is there no place of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be found, whereout may be gathered any proofe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of toongs before the flood. There being then but one, it muſt néedes be the ſame that <hi>Adam</hi> taught his children: as may alſo appéere by this, that all proper names vntill the flood are Hebrue. <hi>Noe</hi> the true ſonne of <hi>Adam</hi> retained and ſpoke this toong, and taught it his children. And although thrée or foure ſcore yéeres before the flood they began to ſpread abroade themſelues, and corruption grew more and more among them (as by that may be gathered, that is written of <hi>Nimrod</hi> and <hi>Aſshur,</hi> and the children of <hi>Cham, Geneſis</hi> the <hi>10.</hi>) yet in the beginning of the eleuenth Chapter Moſes witneſſeth that at what time they, that came to dwell in the plaine of Sennaar, ſpake of building the Citie and Tower afterward called Babel,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:11268:28"/>
all the earth was one la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage &amp; one ſpéech: which I vnderſtand not onely of thoſe that dwelt in the plaine of Sennaar, but of all people then liuing in the world. It is likely that they that came out of the Eaſt countries, and ſetled themſelues in Sennaar were a great number. They ſpake Hebrue, but when confuſion befell their toong, ſome drew one way, others another way, and by continuance of time their Hebrue varying by meanes of their ſeparation was embaſed, and euery ſeuerall people had their language apart. As for ſuch as were not mingled in this diſorder, namely the families of <hi>Sem,</hi> or the moſt part of them, they kept the originall and primitiue toong, wherof <hi>Heber</hi> was the chiefe profeſſour at the confuſion of Babel; and thence it commeth (as it is thought) that the toong was called Hebrue, and the people Hebrues; as <hi>Abraham</hi> in whoſe family that ſpéech remained, is ſurnamed an Hebrue. The Poet, with ſome inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretours, leaues it in doubt whether <hi>Heber</hi> was among the builders of Babel, or dwelt apart. I thinke with ſome others, that he was not of the number, but hearing how the Tower-builders were ſcattered, he gaue the name of <hi>Peleg</hi> (that is, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion) to his ſonne that then was borne: bicauſe (ſaith <hi>Moſes, Geneſ. 10.25.</hi>) that in his time the earth was diuided. Thus much of the Hebrue toong, which was after preſerued by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the high Prieſts, the Iudges, Kings and Prophets. Now let vs conſider what the Poet ſaith further as touching thoſe other toongs, that firſt ariſing of the Hebrue, were after the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion a hundred thouſand waies altered and diſguiſed by the nations liuing aſunder, who themſelues inuented, and carried new words and language, each to the place of their abode.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The firſt langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges deriued from the Hebrue are each of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diuers others.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">17</hi> But ſoftly-ſliding Age, that enuious all doth waſt,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe ancient languages ſoone eu'ry one defac'd</l>
                     <l>That in the thundring ſound of maſons clattring hands,</l>
                     <l>By Tygris banks deuiſ'd, had ouerſpred the lands:</l>
                     <l>And, that the world might be more out of order left,</l>
                     <l>Into a many toongs the leaſt of them hath cleft.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Whence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a toong.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">18</hi> Each language altereth, beit for that marchandiſe</l>
                     <l>Imparting vnto vs the treaſures of great priſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:11268:28"/>From azur'd Amphitrite, and ſending ours aboord,</l>
                     <l>Bould with a good ſucceſſe, oft changeth word for word:</l>
                     <l>Or that the learned man ingenuouſly endighting</l>
                     <l>With guilt and curled words tricks vp his wanton writing.</l>
                     <l>And hunting after praiſe ſome ſtampe nere ſeene before</l>
                     <l>Sets both on deeds and things, or doth at leaſt reſtore</l>
                     <l>Diſclaimed words to vſe, and makes againe be borne</l>
                     <l>Thoſe that with ouer-age, with rot and mould were worne.</l>
                     <l>With them it falleth out, as with leaues in a wood,</l>
                     <l>One fals, another growes; the words that once were good,</l>
                     <l>And, like faire Lillie floures in greeneſt medow ſtrew'd,</l>
                     <l>Quite through the lerned ſpeech their glittring beuty ſhew'd,</l>
                     <l>Now are not in requeſt; but ſith Court them exiles,</l>
                     <l>Aſham'd they ſhrowd themſelues vnder baſe cottage tiles:</l>
                     <l>And thoſe that long-ago were cenſur'd curiouſly</l>
                     <l>For baſe and counterfait, now paſſe on currantly.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">19</hi> A courage bould led with diſcretion fortunate</l>
                     <l>May licence words to paſſe, although they but of late</l>
                     <l>Were forged in his ſhop, among plants naturall</l>
                     <l>May graffe ſome forraine imps, his language therewithall</l>
                     <l>Enriching more and more, and with a diuers gloſe</l>
                     <l>Enameling his talke, his Muſes taske, or proſe.</l>
                     <l>Some language hath no law, but Vſe head-ſtrong and blinde,</l>
                     <l>That runneth whereſoere the people light as winde</l>
                     <l>Goes headlong driuing it: another cloſely running</l>
                     <l>Within the bounds of Art, hir phraſes frames with cunning:</l>
                     <l>Some one ſtraight waxing old aſſoone as it is borne</l>
                     <l>The cradle hath to graue, another is not worne</l>
                     <l>With file of many yeeres; ſome liueth ill beſted</l>
                     <l>Within a ſtraight precinct for euer priſoned,</l>
                     <l>Another bouldly doth from <hi>Alexanders</hi> altar</l>
                     <l>Among the learned ſtretch vnto the mount <hi>Gibraltar.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Such now the Hebrue toong, the Greeke and Latine be;<note place="margin">Hebrue, Greeke, and Latine the beſt of all toongs.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hebrue, for ſtill ſhe holds, and by hir hand hold we,</l>
                     <l>The Word, the ſacred Word of God thriſe-eternall,</l>
                     <l>And was of Lawes diuine the true originall:</l>
                     <l>The Greeke, as one that hath within hir learned writ</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="48" facs="tcp:11268:29"/>Plainly compriſed all the knowledge of mans wit.</l>
                     <l>And valiant Latine eke, bicauſe hir eloquence</l>
                     <l>By ſword was planted through the worlds circumference.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <div n="17" type="note">
                     <head>17.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But ſoftly-ſliding Age.</hi> The Poet héere entreth into conſideration of other toongs beſide the Hebrue: and ſaith theſe firſt toongs that begun in Babel, being all (as it were) Meſlins of Hebrue, by tract of time are ſo worne out, that each one of them hath engendred a many others, as a man may quickly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, if he conſider the great varietie of ancient people that were before the Gréekes and Latines. It ſhall ſuffiſe at this preſent thus to haue pointed hereat in a word. Who-ſo is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of more, let him caſt his eie vpon the thrée firſt and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Monarchies, and all the diuers nations ſubiect vnto them, and mentioned in the Chronicles of the worlde: the Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all is to be found in the firſt Volume of the Hiſtoricall librarie of <hi>N. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ignier.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="note">
                     <head>18.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Each language altereth.</hi> He ſheweth by diuers reaſons whence commeth the change of toongs. Firſt, the trafficke that one countrey people hath with another, as well by ſea (which he calleth, <hi>Th'azur'd Amphitrite</hi>) as alſo by land, is cauſe why we learne ſome new words, as if we made no leſſe exchange of words than of wares. Secondly, a writer that dares venter, and is deſirous to enrich his mother-toong, decketh it boldly with that which he borroweth of others, ſetteth forgotten words on foote againe, inuenteth new words, colouring and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioning them according. Thirdly, time altereth a ſpéech; as we ſée it doth all things elſe, that we might be forced thereby daily more and more to ſée and confeſſe, that nothing is ſure and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt vnder heauen; and to beate downe alſo the vanitie of mans conceit, who commonly vaunteth himſelfe and taketh pride in ſuch things as haue nothing conſtant in them but their owne vnconſtancie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="note">
                     <head>19.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A courage bold.</hi> This commeth too néere the ſeconde reaſon to be counted a fourth. The French Commentar muſt pardon me; I thinke rather the Poet hauing ſpoken of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Marchandiſe and Time, the right and onely means wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:11268:29"/>
new words and phraſes are firſt brought into a language: here he ſheweth vs how they are accepted, for as before he tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in a worde that the Courts diſlike of old words bred their diſuſe; ſo héere he telleth vs plainly that the authoritie of him, that deuiſeth or vſeth new words, is cauſe of their acceptance: which is afterward confirmed by vſe, <hi>Quem penes arbitrium est, &amp; vis &amp; norma loquendi:</hi> as <hi>Horace</hi> writeth. But foraſmuch as vſe without Art draweth a language head-long into Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme, and ſo out of requeſt, and Art without authoritie of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, ſhutteth it vp in a narrow compaſſe, he ſaith, that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue, Latine, and Gréeke, had all theſe maintaining meanes, whereby they haue continued ſo long, and ſpred ſo far abroad. So beginneth he cunningly to make his paſſage from words and phraſes vnto entire languages, the better to come at length to that excellent diſcourſe, that followeth in the next Section, vpon all the principall toongs now ſpoken or knowen in the world. As for the Hebrue, beſides the perfections aboue menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, he ſaith, in it God hath reuealed his will, and that it is the originall of the diuine Law: both of great force to make the toong farre knowne, and continue long: it had further the Art and knowledge of high Prieſts and Prophets, the wiſedome and ſtate of <hi>Salomon,</hi> &amp; was a long time vſed and accuſtomed to be ſpoke in the famous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monwelth of the Iewes. But theſe bicauſe they belong not vnto that toong onely, but as well to the other two, the Poet here leaueth out. The Gréeke he ſaith, in hir bookes containeth at large all the liberall Sciences: a great cauſe and moſt proper to the Gréeke: the reſt as common to the others are let paſſe. The Latine more graue &amp; forcible than the Gréeke (that was a more neat and wanton toong) was aduanced and continued in requeſt by the Romanes force of armes: whoſe Empire was the greateſt and moſt warlike of all the reſt; and therfore is this cauſe héere onely mentioned, as moſt proper to the Latine toong, and the reſt omitted. Theſe thrée toongs do at this day farre ſurpaſſe all others; but vngodlineſſe and contempt of the true Diuinitie, is cauſe why the Hebrue is not eſtéemed as it deſerueth: the more is it regarded of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that know it. As for the Gréeke, that which is now commonly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:11268:30"/>
is very groſſe. The pure and good Gréeke is contained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bookes of <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle, Zenophon, Demoſthenes, Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, Homer, Euripides, Sophocles, Plutarch, Baſil, Naſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and many others. The Latine, after ſome ignorant and vnlearned men had greatly embaſed it, was reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſet on foote againe within theſe foure-ſcore yéeres, at what time there flouriſhed many great and learned perſonages in Europe, as <hi>Melancthon, Eraſmus, Picus Myrand.</hi> and others: but they come ſhort of that grace and liuelihood that the ancient Latine writers haue: <hi>Cicero, Caeſar, Liuie, Virgill, Horace,</hi> and a number of others wel enough knowne: of whom (as alſo of the moſt excellent authors in other toongs) the Poet here goes about to entreat.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The Poets takes breath to enter afreſh into the next diſcourſe, where by way of a Viſion, he cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly deſcribeth the principall toongs, with their beſt authors.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">20</hi> Tracing theſe latter lines, halfe tyred as I were</l>
                     <l>With this entiſing paine of heau'nly Pallas Lere,</l>
                     <l>Still now and then I ſtrike my chin vpon my breſt,</l>
                     <l>And ſoftly both mine eies begin to cloſe to reſt,</l>
                     <l>Moiſt with Ambroſian dew; knit is my ſenſes band,</l>
                     <l>And fairely ſlides my pen foorth of my fainting hand.</l>
                     <l>Vpon my flattring couch I ſpread my ſelfe againe,</l>
                     <l>And plunge in Lethe-ſtreame all troubles of my braine:</l>
                     <l>There drowne I all my cares, ſaue one, that with no traunce</l>
                     <l>Is diſcontinued, to pleaſe and profit Fraunce.</l>
                     <l>The ſacred Forge of Loue, that me enflamed keepes,</l>
                     <l>Will not let ſleepe my ſoule although my body ſleepes.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">21</hi> And golden-winged Dreame riſing in th'Eaſterne ſhore</l>
                     <l>Foorth at his Chriſt all gate, a little while before</l>
                     <l>The Day-gate opened, into a Valley faire</l>
                     <l>Me led fantaſticall, where day and nights freſh aire,</l>
                     <l>The north windes &amp; the ſouth, the drought &amp; th'Iſes mother</l>
                     <l>The faire daies and the foule, came not one after other:</l>
                     <l>There May did alway raigne, and Zephirus bedight</l>
                     <l>With Roſie coronets, blew nicely day and night</l>
                     <l>A woods ſoft-ruſtling boughes, that bloſſoms ſweet did yeeld</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">A deſcription of the ſeat &amp; image of eloquence.</note>And Oualwiſe bewall'd the flowr-embroidred field.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">22</hi> Iuſt in the midſt of all this Ammel-blooming glade</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:11268:30"/>Raiſd was a mightie Rocke, in footſtall maner made:</l>
                     <l>Vpon the top thereof a braſfe Coloſſe did ſtand,</l>
                     <l>That in the left hand held a flaming fierbrand,</l>
                     <l>An Ewer in the right; out from hir golden toong</l>
                     <l>A thouſand little chaines all ore the medow ſprong,</l>
                     <l>That worlds of hearers drew, fine wrought by ſubtill art,</l>
                     <l>Some linked by the eares, and ſome faſt by the Hart.</l>
                     <l>The Boare lay at hir feete, nor foming, nor enraged,</l>
                     <l>There ſlept the Tigre charm'd, &amp; Beares their fume aſſwaged:</l>
                     <l>The neighbour Hillocks leapt, the Woods reioiced round,</l>
                     <l>Eu'n daunſing as it were at hir ſweete voices ſound.</l>
                     <l>A double circled row of pillers high and dight</l>
                     <l>By cunning workmans hand after the Carian right,</l>
                     <l>With baſes vnderpinn'd for their more ſure foundation,</l>
                     <l>Beſet this rauiſhing Image of ſweete Oration:</l>
                     <l>And foure by foure bore vp amid them one language</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe that flouriſh moſt in this our learned age.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">23</hi> Among the bleſſed wits,<note place="margin">6. The Hebrue.</note> to whom heau'n gaue the grace</l>
                     <l>That they ſhould vnderprop the Hebrue in this place</l>
                     <l>The man whoſe face did ſhine like to a blaſing ſtarre</l>
                     <l>Heau'n-decking, fraying-men; that for a Scepter barre</l>
                     <l>A ſcare, yet budding rod, and in his fingers hent</l>
                     <l>The ten-fold regiſter of Gods Commandement;</l>
                     <l>He guideth Iſrael, he left authoritie</l>
                     <l>Firſt both of proſe and verſe to his poſteritie.</l>
                     <l>Such holy writings as not onely long fore-run</l>
                     <l>The writings of the Greekes, but all that they haue done.</l>
                     <l>The ſecond <hi>Dauid</hi> is, whoſe touch right cunningly</l>
                     <l>Combined with his voice drawes downe ſweete harmony</l>
                     <l>From th'organized heau'ns, on Harpe that ſtill ſhall ſound</l>
                     <l>As long as daies great ſtar ſhall ore our heads go round.</l>
                     <l>Nay farther who can tell, after theſe heau'nly Lights</l>
                     <l>Their Meaſures ended haue, but that the bleſſed Sprights,</l>
                     <l>Chriſts holy champions, at ſound of his accords</l>
                     <l>Shall daunce in honor of th' Almightie Lord of Lords:</l>
                     <l>When many legions of Angels, winged ghoſts,</l>
                     <l>Shall ſing holy, holy, holy, Lord God of hoſts.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:11268:31"/>The third is <hi>Salomon,</hi> whoſe goodly monuments</l>
                     <l>Are wiſely powdred with more ſtore of documents</l>
                     <l>And golden ſentences, than doth his diademe</l>
                     <l>With Diamondes and Pearles, and firy Rubies beame.</l>
                     <l>The fourth is <hi>Amos</hi> ſonne, that hath the Graces all,</l>
                     <l>Deuout and full of threats, graue and Rhetoricall.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">2. The Greeke.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">24</hi> The Greeke <hi>Homer</hi> vpholds, that ſweetely verſifies,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe learned Schoole brought foorth a many companies</l>
                     <l>Of old Philoſophers, that made his cunning plea</l>
                     <l>The world to ouerflow like ſome great Ocean ſea.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Plato</hi> all Diuine, who like the Bird we call</l>
                     <l>The Bird of Paradiſe, ſoyles not himſelfe at all</l>
                     <l>With earth or waters touch; but, more than Hels deſcent</l>
                     <l>Surmounted is by Heau'n, ſurmounts the firmament.</l>
                     <l>And ſmooth <hi>Herodotus;</hi> and he of pleaders Arts</l>
                     <l>The Law, <hi>Demosthenes;</hi> gold-mouthed, king of harts.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">3. The Latine.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">25</hi> Then he of <hi>Anthony</hi> and <hi>Catiline</hi> great foe</l>
                     <l>That lightneth and thundreth, &amp; from whoſe breſt doth flow</l>
                     <l>A thouſand ſtreaming floods, wherin the rareſt wits</l>
                     <l>Daily torment themſelues, ſurpriſ'd with maruaile-fits.</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that can do aſwell as he can plead;</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Salust</hi> full of force; and he that Troy doth lead</l>
                     <l>Againe to Tybers banks, a writer ſent from heau'n,</l>
                     <l>That neuer ſhuts his eies to ſleepe morning nor eu'n,</l>
                     <l>That euer treadeth ſure, alway plaine, alway graue,</l>
                     <l>Shamefac'dly venterous and temperately braue,</l>
                     <l>That ſtill is like himſelfe, and vnlike others all:</l>
                     <l>Theſe beare the ſweete-graue toong was laſt emperiall.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">4. The Italian.</note>Th' Italian founded is on <hi>Boccace</hi> pleaſurous;</l>
                     <l>On <hi>Petrarch</hi> finely dight, bold and ſententious;</l>
                     <l>On <hi>Ariosto</hi> ſmoothe, diuers, in paſſions feirce;</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Taſſo,</hi> worthie man to write heroick verſe,</l>
                     <l>Sharpe, ſhort, fyl'd, figured, with language flowing faſt,</l>
                     <l>The firſt to be eſteem'd albeet he wrote the laſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">5. Th' Arabian.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">27</hi> The language Arabick is mightily ſuſtained</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Auerroës</hi> great, deepe-reaching ſubtill-brained:</l>
                     <l>By faire-ſpoke <hi>Auicen,</hi> and <hi>Eldebag</hi> ſatyricall;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:11268:31"/>By ſmooth <hi>Ibnu-farid,</hi> pleaſant and allegoricall.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">28</hi> The Dutch dependeth on the famous <hi>Michell Buther,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">6. The Dutch.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That <hi>Sleidan</hi> turn'd to Dutch; and next on <hi>Martin Luther.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Witbergs and Iſlebe's fame, and on my <hi>Butrick</hi> next,</l>
                     <l>And laſt of <hi>Peucer</hi> ſweet, that dooble-guilds his text.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">29</hi> Then <hi>Gueuare,</hi> and <hi>Boſcan, Grenade,</hi> and <hi>Gracilas,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">7. The Spaniſh.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>With <hi>Nectar</hi> all diſtaind, that mantleth in the glas</l>
                     <l>Of honny-powring pyth, vphold the Caſtillan,</l>
                     <l>And had not th'ancient grace of ſpeaking Catallan,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oſias</hi> rauiſhed, his learning might haue bore</l>
                     <l>The Spaniſh Lawrel from one of the foreſaid foure.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">30</hi> The ſpeech of Engliſhmen hath for hir ſtrong pillers</l>
                     <l>Three Knights, <hi>Bacon</hi> and <hi>More,</hi> they two Lord Chancellers,<note place="margin">8. Th' Engliſh.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who knitting cloſe their toong raiſ'd it from infancie,</l>
                     <l>And coupled eloquence with skill in policie:</l>
                     <l>Sir <hi>Philip Sydney</hi> third, who like a Cignet ſings</l>
                     <l>Faire Tham'ſes ſwelling waues beating with ſiluer wings:</l>
                     <l>This ſtreame with honour fild his eloquence doth beare</l>
                     <l>Into dame <hi>Thetis</hi> lap, and <hi>Thetis</hi> eu'ry-where.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi rend="sup">31</hi> But what new Sunne is this that beameth on mine eies?</l>
                     <l>What? am I wrapt amongſt the heau'nly companies?<note place="margin">For the fourth piller of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh toong he nameth our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> duly and truly praiſing hir for wiſdome, maintenance of peace, learning, and eloquence.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O what a princely grace! what ſtate emperiall!</l>
                     <l>What pleaſant lightning eies! what face Angelicall!</l>
                     <l>Ye learned daughters of him that all gouerneth,</l>
                     <l>Is't not that <hi>Pallas</hi> wiſe, the great <hi>Elizabeth:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That makes the ſturdie men of England nothing bent</l>
                     <l>For mans empire to change a womans gouernment?</l>
                     <l>Who whiles <hi>Erynnis,</hi> loth to tarry long in Hell,</l>
                     <l>Hir neighbour kingdomes all with fire &amp; ſword doth quell,</l>
                     <l>And whiles the darke affright of tempeſt roring-great</l>
                     <l>Doth to the worlds Carack a fearfull ſhipwracke threat,</l>
                     <l>Holdeth in happie peace hir Iſle, where true beliefe,</l>
                     <l>And honorable lawes are reck'ned of in chiefe:</l>
                     <l>That hath not onely gift of plentie delectable</l>
                     <l>To ſpeake hir mother-toong, but readily is able</l>
                     <l>In Latine, Spaniſh, French, without premeditation,</l>
                     <l>In Greeke, Italian, Dutch, to make as good oration,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:11268:32"/>As Greece can, as can Fraunce, as Rome emperiall,</l>
                     <l>As Rhine, as Arne can, plead in their naturall.</l>
                     <l>O bright pearle of the North, martiall, Mars-conquering,</l>
                     <l>Loue ſtill and cheriſh Arts, and heare the Muſes ſing:</l>
                     <l>And incaſe any time my verſes winged-light</l>
                     <l>Shall ouer th' Ocean ſea to thine Iſle take their flight,</l>
                     <l>And by ſome happie chaunce into that faire hand ſlide,</l>
                     <l>That doth ſo many men with lawfull ſcepter guide:</l>
                     <l>View them with gracious eie and fauourable thought,</l>
                     <l>I want thine eloquence to praiſe thee as I ought.</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">9. The French.</note>
                        <hi rend="sup">32</hi> But what are theſe of Fraunce? this count'nance is vnſhap'd</l>
                     <l>Hence hath the bungler hand of idle Maſon ſcrap'd</l>
                     <l>Onely the harder ſcales of eu'ry rugged knot;</l>
                     <l>'Tis <hi>Clement Marot</hi> ſure that laboureth ſo hot</l>
                     <l>Artiſt like without art, and prickt with <hi>Phaebus</hi> launce</l>
                     <l>Tranſporteth Helicon from Italie to Fraunce.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Marot</hi> I honour thee like as an old Coloſſe</l>
                     <l>All ſoiled, all-to-broke, all ouergrow'n with moſſe,</l>
                     <l>Worne pictures, tombes defac'd, not ſo for their beautie</l>
                     <l>As in deuour regard of their antiquitie.</l>
                     <l>What one this other is I ſcarſe remember me;</l>
                     <l>A cunning one he ſeemes what one ſo ere he be.</l>
                     <l>Still reſt I in ſuſpence, ſomtime he doth appeere</l>
                     <l>To be <hi>Iames Amiot,</hi> ſomtime <hi>Blaſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iginiere.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Ronſard</hi> is the next, that doth of graces wrong</l>
                     <l>The Greeke and Latin both, to grace his mother-toong,</l>
                     <l>And with a courage bould doth mannage happily</l>
                     <l>All kind of argument in proſe and poetrie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>De Mornay</hi> this man is, that combats Atheiſme,</l>
                     <l>Iewes ſtubborne vnbeleefe, and fooliſh Paganiſme,</l>
                     <l>With weapons of their owne, he godly, graue, ſetled,</l>
                     <l>Stifneth ſo well his ſtile, plaine eke and flouriſhed,</l>
                     <l>That pregnant reaſons of his winged words, like darts,</l>
                     <l>Deeply inſtrike themſelues into all gentle harts.</l>
                     <l>Then thus I ſpoke to them. O bright, O goodly wits,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The Poets deſire conſidering the learned writers of Fraunce.</note>Who in moſt happie caſe haue conſecrate your writs</l>
                     <l>To immortalitie! ſith that my feeble ſhoulders</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:11268:32"/>May not among-ye be the French glories vphoulders;</l>
                     <l>Alas! ſith I can ſcarce looke after you ſo hie</l>
                     <l>As is the double mount approching to the skie,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſuffer me at leaſt heere proſtrate to imbrace</l>
                     <l>Your honourable knees, graunt me at-leaſt the grace</l>
                     <l>On your bright-ſhining heads to guirlond Aprils ſpring;</l>
                     <l>Graunt of your gentlenes that theſe baſe tunes I ſing</l>
                     <l>May in your glorie get an euerlaſting glorie,</l>
                     <l>And that alway my verſe may regiſter your ſtorie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They granting my requeſt made ſemblance with their hed,<note place="margin">The end of the Viſion.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>So vaniſhed the vale, and all the pillers fled:</l>
                     <l>So likewiſe had the Dreame with them togither haſted,</l>
                     <l>But that I with mine inke his nimble feathers paſted.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <div n="20" type="note">
                     <head>20.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tracing theſe latter lines.</hi> Before he endeth this Booke or diſcourſe, hauing begun to ſpeake of toongs, and their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon one with another; he taketh thence occaſion to ſet before our eies the thrée principall toongs, Hebrue, Gréeke, and Latine, accompanied with ſixe other greatly now-a-daies eſtéemed throughout all Europe. For this purpoſe, and to enrich his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eme with ſome new ornament, worthie the things he treateth of; he declareth, how being wearie with ouer-watching him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in theſe his former ſtudies, he caſt him on his bed and ſlept; yet ſo as the earneſt deſire he had to delight and profit his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, kept ſtill his ſoule awake; which cauſed him to ſée in his Dreame the Viſion héere following. A fine inuention and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the imitation of the beſt ancient Poets both Gréeke and Latine, who, being to handle matters of great importance, are woont by ſuch deuiſes cunningly to prouoke the readers to mark and giue eare vnto them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="note">
                     <head>21.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And golden-winged Dreame.</hi> Of Dreames and their cauſes hath béen ſpoken ſufficiently in the firſt day of this ſecond Wéeke, intituled <hi>Eden,</hi> Page the <hi>46. 47. 48.</hi> &amp;c. hauing héere to ſpeake of a Dreame cléere and eaſie to be conceiued, he diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth it from ſuch as are darkſome and deceiuable, ſaying it was about the dawning of the day when the golden-winged (that is, the ſwéete, pleaſant, and vntroubled) Dreame came
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:11268:33"/>
foorth at the Chriſtall gate in the Eaſt: as much to ſay, as when the day ſtarre ariſeth, or the morning draweth on, we féele (if we were awake before) ſléepe gently ſeazing on vs, and our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits comming and going as it were thorow chriſtall gates: for then be dreames and viſions cléereſt and beſt diſtinguiſhed; whereas before our meate be fully digeſted, our braine ouerlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with vapors, receiueth but troubleſome impreſſions, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo to and fro, and ſo enterlaced one with another, that in the twinkling of an eie, it frameth a thouſand ſhapes, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vaniſheth away and are no more remembred. Now the Poet ſaith, he was guided (as he thought) into a place moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, which he deſcribeth in few verſes, and it is verie fit for the matter following.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="note">
                     <head>22.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iuſt in the middle point.</hi> Firſt he deſcribeth the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Eloquence: to wit, on a great Rocke, wrought and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in manner of a footeſtall, or baſe for an Image to ſtande on: to ſhew how ſtedfaſt and certaine a thing this excellent gift of God is. Secondly, the reſemblance or Image of Eloquence, he calleth a <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> that is, of ſtature ſurpaſſing all others: which betokeneth thus much, that eloquent and faire ſpoken men go many degrées beyonde others, whom they vſe at their pleaſure, and draw whither they liſt, as the examples of <hi>Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> declare, and many proofes thereof are founde in the holie Scripture. He maketh this Image of Braſſe, which implieth the faire gloſſe, the ſwéete ſounde and ſtrong force of Eloquence; he placeth in the left hand a fire-brand, to ſignifie that learned, true, and faire vttrance maketh men ſée &amp; touch (as it were) the right nature of things: in the right hand an Ewer, bicauſe the ſpéech of the wiſe dampeth and putteth out the flame of paſſions. I might note hereof many examples, but I leaue them for the diligent Reader to ſearch: meaning here to offer him but Annotations, which I feare already are growen too long. The little chaines that come foorth from the Images gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den toong, &amp; draw ſuch a number of hearers by the eares &amp; hart, ſignifie the great power of a wel framed ſpéech: the truth wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of appéereth chiefely in preaching the word, in counſels of graue common wealths-men, and orations of good Magiſtrates and <pb n="85" facs="tcp:11268:33"/>
valiant Captaines. In this maner did the ancient Frenchmen paint &amp; ſet out their <hi>Hercules</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Ognius:</hi> whereupon <hi>Alciat</hi> hath made a pretie Embleme) it is the <hi>180.</hi> expounded at large by <hi>Cl. Minos.</hi> The ſumme of al is, that Eloquence is to be preferred before force. Our Poet aimeth at that deſcription. Further concerning the Bore, the Tygre, and the Beare lying tame at the féete of this Image, it ſignifieth that a pleaſant and learned ſpéech appeaſeth all angrie, cruell, and ſauage men; and euen the maddeſt and moſt brutiſh people in the worlde: it maketh the woods and hils to daunce and leape: that is to ſaie, it mooueth, bendeth &amp; inſtructeth very block-heads, and ſuch as are moſt hard of vnderſtanding; &amp; this may be the meaning of thoſe fained tales of <hi>Amphion, Orpheus, Arion,</hi> and other like. Laſtly, this Image is enuironed with a double ranke of pillers, well and ſtrongly grounded and vnder-pinned, that beare vp in due proportion the nine languages following, each by hir owne chiefe authors &amp; maintainers. For euery pillar was wrought in faſhion of a man, &amp; framed to the countenance of one of their beſt writers in a long gowne, or ſtole. And that is the meaning of the French <hi>a la Cariatide: <hi>After the Carian right:</hi>
                        </hi> as <hi>Vitru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> writeth at large in this firſt Chapter of his firſt booke of <hi>Architecture.</hi> This I note bicauſe the French Commentar lets it paſſe and it troubled my ſelfe to vnderſtand it at the firſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="note">
                     <head>23.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Among the bleſſed wits.</hi> For chiefe props of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue toong (which he placeth in the fore front of Eloquence, as in euery regard it was méete, whether we conſider the ſwéete grauitie, the naturall impliance, the ſhortnes, hautines, liuely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of it, or the ſinceritie, holines, light, and heauenly maieſtie) he nameth firſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> bicauſe he is the moſt ancient of thoſe whoſe writings in this toong are extant. As for the booke of the Propheſie of <hi>Henoch,</hi> it was loſt a long time ago. He deſcribeth this holy Law-writer after an excellent manner, as was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in a diſcourſe of Eloquence. His face ſhineth like a blaſing Starre: alluding to that in the Scripture that <hi>Moſes</hi> comming downe from the mount where he had talked with God, his face ſo ſhined, that none was able to behold his countenance; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:11268:34"/>
as he was faine to weare a vaile ouer it: the reſt is verie eaſie to be vnderſtood, eſpecially of ſuch as haue neuer ſo lightlie turned ouer the Hiſtorie. Now for the bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they were written many hundred yéeres before the Gréekes were knowne: who were not heard of in the world but a little before the raigne of <hi>Saul,</hi> and had but few works in writing, or none at all, till after the time of <hi>Salomon,</hi> as their owne Hiſtories witnes, whoſoeuer will take paines to turne them ouer. Naie further, all their knowledge came from the Egyptians, Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicians and others, who had learned ſomewhat by conuerſing with the Hebrues. And to come againe to <hi>Moſes,</hi> he hath béene in maruellous account with infinite Heathen writers. If any haue lightly regarded, or found fault with him, it was either bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they vnderſtood him not at all, or maliced him excéedingly, which a man may eaſily finde in their writings. The ſecond au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Hebrue he counteth <hi>Dauid,</hi> whoſe Pſalmes he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much of in few lines, but little it is in compariſon of their excellencie, wherof many ancient and late writers haue ſpoken notable things: I will not heape them vp here, aſſuring my ſelfe that all true Chriſtians will grant me that the Booke of <hi>Dauids</hi> Pſalmes is (as Saint <hi>Baſill</hi> ſaith) the Storehouſe and treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of all good learning, for all men to come at; and will confeſſe with Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> and S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that nothing better becommeth a man, be he Peaſant or Crafteſ-man, great or ſmall, than to ſing vnto the Lord the praiſes and thankeſgiuing in theſe excellent ſongs contained: the very liuely and true Anatomies of a beléeuing ſoule. O how curſed and abominable before God and his Church are thoſe wicked ones, that haue forbidden Chriſtians the vnderſtanding and vſe of them, and baniſhed them out of Chriſtendom: that haue ſuffred, allowed, maintained, commanded and commended vnto the people theſe ſhamefull and wanton Poeſies, theſe bookes of vanitie, error, &amp; leaſings, which with their authors deſerue the fire: and not the quiet and peaceable perſons, that call vpon Ieſus Chriſt, and beléeue ſtedfaſtly the life euerlaſting. The ſoule that feareth God will not take this my digreſſion ill, nor thinke it néedleſſe:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:11268:34"/>
As for the vngodly, let them ſpit at it, if they will, I regarde them not. The thirde authour and ornament of the Hebrue is reckoned <hi>Salomon</hi> in his Prouerbes, the booke of the Preacher, and the Song of Songs, bookes more beſprinckled with golden words and notable ſentences, than his crowne was with preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones and pearles emboſſed. Happie is the man that taketh delight to marke and daily thinke vpon ſo profitable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie inſtructions. The fourth is the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Amos,</hi> right ſuch a one as the Poet hath deſcribed. Theſe foure he thought ſufficient to name, bicauſe they haue moſt writings extant, and are withall excéeding eloquent, as might eaſilie be prooued by particulars, if I were to write a Commentarie, or a whole diſcourſe thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="note">
                     <head>24.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Greeke. Homer,</hi> his <hi>Illias</hi> and <hi>Odyſſea</hi> contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>48.</hi> bookes, is the moſt ancient Gréeke Auctor we haue: his inuentions are wonderfull, his vaine naturall, his verſes ſmoothe, and full of Art, and the more they are conſidered, the greater grace they haue. There is alſo in them a hidden ſenſe, and the very welſpring of all humane knowledge; as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>péere by that infinite péeces of his poeſies are cited in the bookes of ancient &amp; late Philoſophers, Geographers, Hiſtoriographers and Orators, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> and others witnes. The next to <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> is <hi>Plato,</hi> not in time but in worthines: he is called the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Philoſopher, bicauſe he is ſo maruellous pure, ſo high &amp; loftie in al his diſcourſes; the true ſcholler of him that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelfe to know but one thing, namely that he knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, declared that he knew all things that might be learned in the worlde, as touching the worlde. For concerning the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſaluation, <hi>Plato</hi> and his maiſter both were ignorant: and ſith all other knowledge is nothing in compariſon of that, (the more are we bound to God that haue it) he ſaid moſt truly, that he knew nothing. The third is <hi>Herodotus,</hi> who writeth in th' Ionick Dialect, that is a kinde of Gréeke differing a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in phraſes and pronuntiation from the common-ſpoken, as ſome farre ſcituate ſhires do from the Court or mother Citie of their Countrie: in diuers points it agréeth with the French.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:11268:35"/>
                        <hi>Plutarch</hi> dealeth ſomewhat too roughly with this woorthy Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriographer, in whoſe defence I will oppoſe the authoritie of a learned man of our time: who in a certaine Preface of his, ſaith of <hi>Herodotus: <hi>Narrationes eius ſunt diſertae, indicationes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſae, ſpecioſae, explicationes accuratae &amp; euidentes, collectiones certa atque plenae, in his rerum gestarum, hominum, temporum fides, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata compertorum relatio, dubiorum coniectura ſagax, fabuloſorum verecunda commemoratio, mira vbi<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> ſimplicitas, &amp; eximius quidam candor.</hi>
                        </hi> Sée the great praiſes, and perfections of a graue Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographer. The fourth is <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> the prince of Gréeke Orators, the very rule and ſquare of all that endeuour to ſpeake eloquently, a man that leadeth other mens mindes as he liſt, excellent in all his diſcourſes: which are extant, the moſt of them, and read to the great vſe and profit of thoſe that know how to applie them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="note">
                     <head>25.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then he of Anthonie and Catiline great foe.</hi> That is <hi>Cicero,</hi> ſurnamed the father of Eloquence: he is the firſt and chiefe of thoſe that grace and maintaine the Latine toong. He was extremely hated of <hi>Marke Anthonie</hi> and <hi>Catiline,</hi> both whom he hath alſo bitterly purſued and touched to the quicke, as his Catilinarie and Philippick Orations declare: the often printing of his works, and learned mens continuall reading of them, and borrowing thence the beſt graces of their writings, do prooue his learning, eloquence and plentie of ſpéech to be ſuch as the Poet héere deſcribeth. The ſecond is <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the moſt vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant of eloquent men, and moſt eloquent of valiant men, as may well appéere by his life in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and his Commentaries <hi>de bello Gallico:</hi> by which worke he hath wrung the pen out of learned mens hands, and in a maner diſcouraged them al from writing Hiſtories, bicauſe they ſée ſuch perfection therein, as they are not able to come néere. The third is the Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher <hi>Saluſt:</hi> we haue of his works, beſides diuers Orations, two Hiſtories remaining, <hi>Coniuratio Catilinae: &amp; bellum Iugur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinum,</hi> ſhort they are, but full of ſentence and ſinewes, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ancient force and vigor of the Roman toong. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may hereto adde the commendations of theſe thrée authors,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:11268:35"/>
as they are in many learned bookes of late writers here and there ſcattered. As for thoſe that thinke <hi>Cicero</hi> bableth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out learning, and that <hi>Caeſar</hi> the Dictatour and firſt Emperour wrote not theſe Commentaries that beare his name, and that <hi>Saluſt</hi> writeth a hard and forced ſtile: bicauſe their accuſations are falſe, and they ſo farre out of the way, I thinke them woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie none other anſwere, than our Poets few verſes here. Of the fourth, which is the Poet <hi>Virgil:</hi> too much cannot be ſpoken: his bookes of <hi>Georgickes</hi> and <hi>Aeneidos,</hi> being ſuch maruellous works, and ſo farre excéeding all other bookes of humanitie: I ſpeake not onely for the excellence of his verſe; but ſure in the depth of his inuentions, his iudgement, his decence, his mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, his grauitie, and his ſtate, how much he doth outſtrip and go beyond al others, may be ſéene not onely in euery booke of his, but euen in euery verſe; wherein is contained a thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſecrets, and as it were the abridgement of all kind of Arts and knowledge; beſides his proper tearmes, his Epythites al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way fit, his metaphors and figures ſow'n and ſprinkled in their right places, and his ſpéech quite throughout eloquent and pure, without any bodging or dawberie whatſoeuer. The learned <hi>Caeſar Scaliger</hi> among many others, hath plainly and at large declared in his Art of Poetrie, the excellencie of this Authour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="note">
                     <head>26.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Th' Italian.</hi> For ornament of the Italian, a language riſen of the Roman or Latine, he nameth thrée Poets and one Orator, ſlipping diuers writers of hiſtorie &amp; Secretaries, that haue left diuers excellent works, Orations, and Epiſtles among vs. The reaſon is (I thinke) bicauſe theſe foure containe in them all the graces of the others. He nameth alſo the Tuſcan toong, bicauſe of all the diuers Dialects of Italie the <hi>Luquiſh, Milaniſh, Geneuiſh,</hi> and <hi>Venetian,</hi> none are ſo pure and fine as the Florentine or Tuſcan. <hi>Iohn Boccace</hi> hath written long time agoe, but a very fine and pure ſtile; as his <hi>Decameron,</hi> his <hi>Fiametta,</hi> the <hi>Philocope, The Laberinth,</hi> and his other bookes wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that with the world are in ſo great requeſt. <hi>Frauncis Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch</hi> hath written ſince, and inuented goodly words, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his owne pregnant wit, partly by imitation of all the beſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:11268:36"/>
Auctors, hath enriched the toong with many graces: he hath ventured alſo far and made Sonets, Chapters, and Cantoes wonderfull curious. Then <hi>Ludouico Arioſto</hi> of Ferara hath ſet foorth a legend of Loue, entituled <hi>Orlando furioſo,</hi> in verſes ſwéete and méete, famous throughout all Italie, he is full of affections in his diſcourſe, and as delightfull as is poſſible, by reaſon of the varietie of that fabulous matter he writeth of, which he ſhadoweth ſo cunningly, that the reader is therewith often affected and mooued, as if it were a true ſtorie, or at leaſt not altogither falſe. <hi>Torquato Taſſo</hi> is laſt of the foure in time of writing, but in account (as the Poet ſaith) the firſt and chiefe: he was the ſonne of <hi>Bernardo Taſſo</hi> that eloquent man, whoſe excellent Epiſtles are in print. This his ſonne hath written in twenty books or Cantoes, of ſtately verſe a poeme, the beſt of all Italians, entituled <hi>Gieruſalemme liberata,</hi> all the graces and riches of the Gréekes and Latines are there gathered togither, and wrought into it after the beſt maner, ſo graue, ſo ſhort, ſo learned, ſo comely, ſo liuely, ſo ſtately, as if it were the worke of another <hi>Virgil.</hi> There are alſo Printed at Ferrara, thrée vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes of his works, containing other kindes of verſe, and all ſorts of fine inuentions, a Comedie, a Tragedie, diuers Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues and diſcourſes in proſe, all are woorth reading, and all make good the iudgement that our Poet hath giuen of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="note">
                     <head>27.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The language Arabike.</hi> This language is comen of the Hebrue: among other learned mens bookes that haue made this toong of account, we haue the works of <hi>Aben Roïs,</hi> that is, the ſonne of kings: for <hi>Ben</hi> ſignifieth <hi>a ſonne,</hi> in Hebrue; and the Arabians adde to the beginning this prepoſition <hi>A,</hi> and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <hi>Al.</hi> This <hi>Aben Roïs</hi> is the ſame that we commonly call <hi>Auerroës,</hi> the Commentar, a very excellent Philoſopher. He hath commented vpon moſt of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and is tranſlated into Latine, printed at Venice; the worke doth ſhew the déepe reach and ſubtill braine of the man. <hi>Auicen</hi> was a great Philoſopher and Phyſition, as his writings alſo declare. <hi>Geſner</hi> ſaith <hi>Auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roës</hi> was of Cordway, and <hi>Auicen</hi> of Seuill, and ſo I thinke:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:11268:36"/>
but it appéereth by their works that they were both Arabians, and profeſſed the ſuperſtition of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> As for <hi>Eldebag, Iohannes Leo</hi> writeth of him in the fift booke of his deſcription of Affrike. This poet borne at Malaga in Grenade, of great name thorough all the parts of Buggie and Thunes, was very eloquent in the Arabian toong, and wonderfull ſharpe in railing on thoſe that did him hurt: he made the men of Tebeſſe féele it in a Satyre he wrote againſt them, the effect whereof is this: that Nature knowing the Tebeſſians ſhould be men of little worth and very ſwine, woulde make no good thing growe about their citie but nuts. The laſt, to wit, <hi>Ibnu-farid,</hi> the French Commentar knoweth not what he was, and I can not learne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="note">
                     <head>28.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Dutch.</hi> For the Dutch or Almaine toong he ſetteth vs downe <hi>Mychaell Beuther,</hi> who very well hath tranſlated the Latine Commentaries of <hi>Sleidan:</hi> the next is <hi>Luther</hi> borne at <hi>Iſlebe,</hi> as learned and eloquent a man as any was among the Diuines and Preachers of Germanie, as all will confeſſe, that haue read his works in Dutch: he Preached and read Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the ſpace of many yéeres at Wytteberg in Saxony. Then <hi>Gaſper Peucer</hi> ſonne in law to <hi>Phillip Melancthon,</hi> an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Philoſopher, Mathematician, and Phiſition, as his works declare. And laſtly <hi>Peter Beutrick,</hi> Counſeller to Duke <hi>Iohn Caſimer,</hi> and chiefe dealer for him with diuers Princes; lately deceaſed. I could name you many more, but I content my ſelfe, as the Poet hath done, with theſe foure.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="note">
                     <head>29.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then Gueuare.</hi> The bookes of <hi>Anthony de Gueuare, du Boſcan, de Grenade, de Gracylace,</hi> haue béene for the moſt part, tranſlated into Latine, Italian and French: but they are far better in their Caſtilian: which is the moſt pure Dialect of the Spaniſh toong, and wherein the men of learning and good nourriture are woont ordinarily to write and ſpeake. And theſe foure the Poet hath choſen for the moſt eloquent writers in this toong: yet nothing foredéeming diuers others that haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten well both in verſe and proſe; as namely <hi>Oſias,</hi> whom but for his old Dialect, he iudgeth as good an author as the other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="note">
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:11268:37"/>
                     <head>30.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The ſpeech of Engliſh.</hi> For ornament of the Engliſh toong he nameth ſir <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> and ſir <hi>Nicholas Bacon</hi> both Lord Chauncellors: the firſt of them was very learned in the Arts and toongs: the ſecond excéeding well ſéene in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lawes of England: and both very eloquent in their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language. As for ſir <hi>Philip Sidney</hi> he deſerueth no leſſe commendation than the Poet hath giuen him. <hi>Chaucer</hi> deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the like commendation here that <hi>Oſias</hi> did among the Spaniſh Auctors.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="note">
                     <head>31.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But what new Sunne is this.</hi> He maketh a digreſſion in praiſe of the Quéene of England, who the ſpace of ſeuen and thirtie yéeres hath gouerned hir Realme in great proſperitie; ſo as, during the troubles and ouerthrowes of other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes about hir, hir ſelfe and hir people haue béene preſerued from infinite dangers. This famous Quéene hath alſo the toongs héere mentioned by the Poet, very parfit, and at this day by the ſingular grace of God ſhe is accounted the pretious pearle of the North, and very fortunate in all the wars ſhe taketh in hand: hir happie ſucceſſe and victories are euery way ſo memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that they deſerue to be written in a large hiſtorie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced of all poſteritie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="note">
                     <head>32.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But what are theſe of Fraunce? Clement Marot</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be admired for his time, in regard of the ignorance and barbariſme that raigned in Europe many yéeres before him, hath led the Muſes ouer the Alpes, and araied them after the French faſhion: as witneſſeth, among other his works, the tranſlation of nine and fortie Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid,</hi> a worke that will continue in account as long as Yea and Nay are ſpoken, euen to the worlds end. Indéede he wanteth that Art and thoſe fine deuiſes that ſome later writers haue; but euen in this want &amp; theſe imperfections he hath done woonderous well; &amp; ſheweth in his naturall vaine that if he had ſiſt he could haue béene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent: yea in ſome points and places he hath ſo done alreadie, as the beſt of them all could haue done no better. For tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we haue <hi>Iacques Amiot,</hi> who hath turned into French the Ethiopian Hiſtorie of <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> ſeuen bookes of <hi>Diodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:11268:37"/>
Siculus,</hi> and all <hi>Plutarch,</hi> wherein he hath laboured to very good purpoſe, and with happie ſucceſſe: I would to God he had ſet his hand alſo to <hi>Thucidides, Xenophon,</hi> and <hi>Seneca:</hi> his ſtile is pure, and naturall, not affected, not forced; right good and true French. <hi>Blaſe Viginere</hi> hath alſo tranſlated manie bookes, as the Polonian hiſtorie, a part of <hi>Liuie, Caeſar, Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condylas, Philoſtratus,</hi> thrée Dialogs of Friendſhip, and the Pſalmes in frée verſe, all which I haue read ouer and againe, yet doe I prefer <hi>Amiot</hi> before him. Indéede I finde in <hi>Viginere</hi> a very ready ſtile and matter well choſen, but the other (I know not how) me thinks hath a better carriage of himſelfe. The <hi>Seiour de Vaupriuas</hi> in his French Librarie ſaith, of all the foſter-children of the Muſes that were bred in Fraunce <hi>Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere</hi> hath ſo written, that, as well for learning as for eloquence of ſpéech, he hath preuented all that ſhall come after him, and as it were ſhut the gate againſt them. Sée what a commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion héere is: I leaue the Reader to iudge of our opinions. Our Poet ſtaieth in doubt, but I haue béene bould to go further; I truſt without any great offence: in this conſiſteth not the good or bad ſtate of Fraunce. Concerning Poets, he nameth <hi>Peter Ronſard,</hi> who hath made himſelfe rich with Gréeke and Latine ſpoiles, as his Treatiſes of Loue, his diuers Poemes, his Odes, Elegies, and Hymnes doe witnes: wherein a man may reade all ſort of verſes, and all kinde of matter, ſometimes in a lowe ſtile, ſometimes in a meane, ſometimes in a loftie ſtile: For which cauſe the Poet calleth him Great <hi>Ronſard.</hi> I will note héere a notable ſpéech of his: after our Poets firſt Wéeke was come foorth in print, being aſked his opinion of the worke, he anſwered, alluding to the title, <hi>Mounſeiur du Bartas</hi> hath done more in one wéeke than I haue done in all my life time. As for <hi>Philip de Mornay,</hi> Lord of Pleſſie Marly, his learned worke of the truth of Chriſtian religion, honoured thus by the true title, and written in good French, with liuely reaſons there gathered togither, mooueth and draweth to his purpoſe, that is, to acknowledge the truth, all that read it with a hart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of peace and good. The like may be ſaid of his Diſcourſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:11268:38"/>
of life and death, of his Treatiſe of the Church, his Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſome Epiſtles and Demonſtrations of his. For all his writings are ſtrengthened with arguments, inductions, and proofes inuincible, and all in a ſtile with grauitie &amp; ſwéetnes mixed, well knit, and well ſounding, and eaſie enough to thoſe that are neuer ſo little acquainted with it. The Poet hauing ſo liuely repreſented his Viſion, endeth his diſcourſe of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and hir moſt renowmed fauourers in euery language, and ſo ſhutteth vp his ſixt Booke: Which is the ſecond of the ſecond day of his ſecond Wéeke.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11268:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
